<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aurora Containing the first fancies of the authors youth, VVilliam Alexander of Menstrie.</title>
            <author>Stirling, William Alexander, Earl of, 1567 or 8-1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 150 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16457</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 337</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100493</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836333</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836333</idno>
            <idno type="VID">598</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16457)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 598)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 818:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Aurora Containing the first fancies of the authors youth, VVilliam Alexander of Menstrie.</title>
                  <author>Stirling, William Alexander, Earl of, 1567 or 8-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[94] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Field for Edward Blount,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-M⁴.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Probably issued as part of: The monarchick tragedies: London, 1604.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:598:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:598:1"/>
            <p>AVRORA. Containing the firſt fancies of the <hi>Authors youth,</hi> VVilliam Alexander of Menſtrie.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Richard Field (McKerrow 192): "framed device of an anchor suspended by a hand from the clouds"</figDesc>
               <head>ANCHORA SPEI</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by RICHARD FIELD for <hi>Edward Blount.</hi> 1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:598:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:598:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE AND VERTVOVS Lady, the Lady Agnes Dowglas <hi>Counteſſe of Argyle.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAME, when I remember the manie obligations which I owe to your manifold merits, I often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times accuſe my ſelfe to my ſelf, of forgetfulnes, and yet I am to be excuſed: for how can I ſatisfie ſo infinit a debt, ſince whilſt I go to diſengage my ſelf in ſome meaſure, by giuing you the patronage of theſe vnpoliſhed lines (which indeed to their manie errors, had need of a reſpected Sanctuary) I but engage my ſelf further, while as you take the patronage of ſo vnpoliſhed lines. Yet this ſhall not diſcourage me, for alwayes I carie this aduantage, that as they were the fruits of beautie, ſo ſhal they be ſacrificed as oblations to beautie. And to a beautie, though of it ſelfe moſt happie, yet more happie in this, that it is thought worthie (and can be no more then worthy) to be the outward couer
<pb facs="tcp:598:3"/>of ſo many inward perfections. So aſſuring my ſelfe, that as no darkneſſe can abide before the Sunne, ſo no deformitie can be found in thoſe papers, ouer which your eyes haue once ſhined. I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors moſt humbly deuoted, <hi>William Alexander.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb facs="tcp:598:3"/>
            <head>AVRORA.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sonet</hi> 1.</head>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hil'ſt charming fancies moue me to reueale</l>
               <l>The idle rauings of my brain-ſicke youth,</l>
               <l>My heart doth pant within, to heare my mouth</l>
               <l>Vnfold the follies which it would conceale:</l>
               <l>Yet bitter <hi>Critickes</hi> may miſtake my mind;</l>
               <l>Not beautie, no, but vertue raiſd my fires,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſacred flame did cheriſh chaſt deſires,</l>
               <l>And through my cloudie fortune clearely ſhin'd.</l>
               <l>But had not others otherwiſe aduiſd,</l>
               <l>My cabinet ſhould yet theſe ſcroles containe,</l>
               <l>This childiſh birth of a conceitie braine,</l>
               <l>Which I had ſtill as trifling toyes deſpiſd:</l>
               <l>Pardon thoſe errours of mine vnripe age;</l>
               <l>My tender Muſe by time may grow more ſage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sonet</hi> 2.</head>
               <l>AS yet three luſters were not quite expir'd,</l>
               <l>Since I had bene a partner of the light,</l>
               <l>When I beheld a face, a face more bright</l>
               <l>Then gliſtring <hi>Phoebus</hi> when the fields are fir'd:</l>
               <l>Long time amaz'd rare beautie I admir'd,</l>
               <l>The beames reflecting on my captiu'd ſight,</l>
               <l>Till that ſurpriz'd (I wot not by what flight)</l>
               <l>More then I could conceiue my ſoule deſir'd,</l>
               <l>My takers ſtate I long'd for to compriſe.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:4"/>
               <l>For ſtill I doubted who had made the rape,</l>
               <l>If t'was a bodie or an airie ſhape,</l>
               <l>With fain'd perfections for to mocke the eyes:</l>
               <l>At laſt I knew t'was a moſt diuine creature,</l>
               <l>The Crowne of th'Earth, th'excellencie of Nature.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 3.</head>
               <l>THat ſubtill Greeke who for t'aduance his art,</l>
               <l>Shap'd Beauties Goddeſſe with ſo ſweet a grace,</l>
               <l>And with a learned penſill limn'd her face,</l>
               <l>Till all the world admir'd the workmans part.</l>
               <l>Of ſuch whom Fame did moſt accompliſh'd call</l>
               <l>The naked ſnowes he ſeuerally perceiued,</l>
               <l>Then drew th'<hi>Idaea</hi> which his ſoule conceiued,</l>
               <l>Of that which was moſt exquiſite in all:</l>
               <l>But had thy forme his fancie firſt poſſeſt,</l>
               <l>If worldly knowledge could ſo high attaine,</l>
               <l>Thou mightſt haue ſpar'd the curious Painters paine,</l>
               <l>And ſatisfide him more then all the reſt.</l>
               <l>O if he had all thy perfections noted,</l>
               <l>The Painter with his Picture ſtraight had doted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Song.</hi> 1.</head>
               <l>O Would to God a way were found,</l>
               <l>That by ſome ſecret ſympathie vnknowne,</l>
               <l>My Faire my fancies depth might ſound,</l>
               <l>And know my ſtate as clearely as her owne.</l>
               <l>Then bleſt, moſt bleſt were I,</l>
               <l>No doubt beneath the skie</l>
               <l>I were the happieſt wight:</l>
               <l>For if my ſtate they knew,</l>
               <l>It ruthleſſe rockes would rue,</l>
               <l>And mend me if they might.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:4"/>
               <l>But as the babe before the wand,</l>
               <l>Whoſe faultleſſe part his parents will not truſt,</l>
               <l>For very feare doth trembling ſtand,</l>
               <l>And quakes to ſpeake although his cauſe be iuſt:</l>
               <l>So ſet before her face,</l>
               <l>Though bent to pleade for grace,</l>
               <l>I wot not how I faile:</l>
               <l>Yet minding to ſay much,</l>
               <l>That ſtring I neuer touch,</l>
               <l>But ſtand diſmaid and pale.</l>
               <l>The deepeſt riuers make leaſt din,</l>
               <l>The ſilent ſoule doth moſt abound in care:</l>
               <l>Then might my breſt be read within,</l>
               <l>A thouſand volumes would be written there.</l>
               <l>Might ſilence ſhew my mind,</l>
               <l>Sighes tell how I were pin'd,</l>
               <l>Or lookes my woes relate;</l>
               <l>Then any pregnant wit,</l>
               <l>That well remarked it,</l>
               <l>Would ſoone diſcerne my ſtate.</l>
               <l>No fauour yet my Faire affoords,</l>
               <l>But looking haughtie, though with humble eyes,</l>
               <l>Doth quite confound my ſtaggering words;</l>
               <l>And as not ſpying that thing which ſhe ſpies.</l>
               <l>A mirror makes of me,</l>
               <l>Where ſhe her ſelfe may ſee:</l>
               <l>And what ſhe brings to paſſe,</l>
               <l>I trembling too for feare,</l>
               <l>Moue neither eye nor eare,</l>
               <l>As if I were her glaſſe.</l>
               <l>Whilſt in this manner I remaine,</l>
               <l>Like to the ſtatue of ſome one that's dead,</l>
               <l>Strange tyrants in my boſome raigne,</l>
               <l>A field of fancies fights within my head:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:5"/>
               <l>Yet if the tongue were true,</l>
               <l>We boldly might purſue</l>
               <l>That Diamantine hart.</l>
               <l>But when that it's reſtraind,</l>
               <l>As doom'd to be diſdaind,</l>
               <l>My ſighes ſhew how I ſmart.</l>
               <l>No wonder then although I wracke,</l>
               <l>By them betrayd in whom I did confide,</l>
               <l>Since tongue, heart, eyes and all gaue backe,</l>
               <l>She iuſtly may my childiſhneſſe deride.</l>
               <l>Yet that which I conceale,</l>
               <l>May ſerue for to reueale</l>
               <l>My feruencie in loue.</l>
               <l>My paſſions were too great,</l>
               <l>For words t'expreſſe my ſtate,</l>
               <l>As to my paines I proue.</l>
               <l>Oft thoſe that do deſerue diſdaine,</l>
               <l>For forging fancies get the beſt reward:</l>
               <l>Where I who feele what they do faine,</l>
               <l>For too much loue am had in no regard.</l>
               <l>Behold by proofe we ſee</l>
               <l>The gallant liuing free,</l>
               <l>His fancies doth extend:</l>
               <l>Where he that is orecome,</l>
               <l>Rain'd with reſpects ſtands dumbe,</l>
               <l>Still fearing to offend.</l>
               <l>My baſhfulneſſe when ſhe beholds,</l>
               <l>Or rather my affection out of bounds,</l>
               <l>Although my face my ſtate vnfolds,</l>
               <l>And in my hew diſcouers hidden wounds:</l>
               <l>Yet ieaſting at my wo,</l>
               <l>She doubts if it be ſo,</l>
               <l>As ſhe could not conceiue it.</l>
               <l>This grieues me moſt of all,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:5"/>
               <l>She triumphs in my fall,</l>
               <l>Not ſeeming to perceiue it.</l>
               <l>Then ſince in vaine I plaints impart</l>
               <l>To ſcornfull eares, in a contemned ſcroule;</l>
               <l>And ſince my toung betrayes my hart,</l>
               <l>And cannot tell the anguiſh of my ſoule:</l>
               <l>Hencefoorth Ile hide my loſſes,</l>
               <l>And not recompt the croſſes</l>
               <l>That do my ioyes orethrow:</l>
               <l>At leaſt to ſenſleſſe things,</l>
               <l>Mounts, vales, woods, flouds, and ſprings,</l>
               <l>I ſhall them onely ſhow.</l>
               <l>Ah vnaffected lines,</l>
               <l>True models of my heart,</l>
               <l>The world may ſee, that in you ſhines</l>
               <l>The power of paſſion more then art.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 4.</head>
               <l>ONce to debate my cauſe whilſt I drew neere,</l>
               <l>My ſtaggering toung againſt me did conſpire,</l>
               <l>And whilſt it ſhould haue charg'd, it did retire,</l>
               <l>A certaine ſigne of loue that was ſincere:</l>
               <l>I ſaw her heauenly vertues ſhine ſo cleere,</l>
               <l>That I was forc'd for to conceale my fire,</l>
               <l>And with reſpects euen bridling my deſire.</l>
               <l>More then my life I held her honour deere,</l>
               <l>And though I burn'd with all the flames of loue,</l>
               <l>Yet frozen with a reuerent kind of feares,</l>
               <l>I durſt not poure my paſſions in her eares;</l>
               <l>Leſt ſo I might the hope I had remoue.</l>
               <l>Thus Loue mar'd loue, Deſire deſire reſtrain'd;</l>
               <l>Of mind to moue a world, I dumbe remain'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 5.</head>
               <l>NO wonder though that this my bliſſe diſmaies,</l>
               <l>Whilſt rendred vp to neuer-pleas'd deſires,</l>
               <l>I burne, and yet muſt couer curſed fires,</l>
               <l>Whoſe flame it ſelfe againſt my will bewrayes.</l>
               <l>Sometimes my faire to launce my wound aſſayes,</l>
               <l>And with th'occaſion as it ſeemes conſpires,</l>
               <l>And indirectly oft my ſtate inquires,</l>
               <l>Which I would hide whilſt it it ſelfe betrayes.</l>
               <l>If that a guiltie geſture did diſcloſe</l>
               <l>The hideous horrors that my ſoule contain'd,</l>
               <l>Or wandring words deriu'd from inward woes,</l>
               <l>Did tell my ſtate, their treaſon I diſdain'd:</l>
               <l>And I could wiſh to be but as I am,</l>
               <l>If that ſhe knew how I conceale the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sonet</hi> 6.</head>
               <l>HVge hoſts of thoughts imbattled in my breſt,</l>
               <l>Are euer buſied with inteſtine warres,</l>
               <l>And like to <hi>Cadmus</hi> earth-borne troupes at iarres,</l>
               <l>Haue ſpoil'd my ſoule of peace, themſelues of reſt.</l>
               <l>Thus forc'd to reape ſuch ſeed as I haue ſowne,</l>
               <l>I (hauing intereſt in this doubtfull ſtrife)</l>
               <l>Hope much, feare more, doubt moſt, vnhappie life.</l>
               <l>What euer ſide preuaile, I'm ſtill orethrowne:</l>
               <l>O neither life nor death! ô both, but bad</l>
               <l>Imparadiz'd, whiles in mine owne conceit,</l>
               <l>My fancies ſtraight againe imbroyle my ſtate,</l>
               <l>And in a moment make me glad and ſad.</l>
               <l>Thus neither yeelding quite to this nor that,</l>
               <l>I liue, I die, I do I wot not what.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 7.</head>
               <l>A Flame of loue that glaunceth in thoſe eyes,</l>
               <l>Where maieſtie with ſweetneſſe mixt remaines,</l>
               <l>Doth poure ſo ſweet a poyſon in the veines,</l>
               <l>That who them viewes ſtraight wounded wondring dyes.</l>
               <l>But yet who would not looke on thoſe cleare skies,</l>
               <l>And loue to periſh with ſo pleaſant paines,</l>
               <l>While as thoſe lights of loue hide beauties traine</l>
               <l>With iuorie Orbes, where ſtill two ſtarres ariſe:</l>
               <l>When as thoſe chriſtall Comets whiles appeare,</l>
               <l>Eye-rauiſh'd I go gazing on their rayes,</l>
               <l>Whilſt they enrich'd with many princely prayes,</l>
               <l>Ore hoſts of hearts triumphing ſtill retire:</l>
               <l>Thoſe planets when they ſhine in their owne kinds,</l>
               <l>Do boaſt t'orethrow whole monarchies of minds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 8.</head>
               <l>AH what diſaſtrous fortune haue I had!</l>
               <l>Lo ſtill in league with all that may annoy,</l>
               <l>And entred in enimitie with Ioy,</l>
               <l>I entertaine all things that make me ſad,</l>
               <l>With many miſeries almoſt gone mad:</l>
               <l>To purchaſe paines I all my paines employ,</l>
               <l>And vſe all meanes my ſelfe for to deſtroy,</l>
               <l>The tenour of my ſtarre hath bene ſo bad.</l>
               <l>And though my ſtate a thouſand times were worſe,</l>
               <l>As it is elſe paſt bounds of all beleefe:</l>
               <l>Yet all <hi>Pandora's</hi> plagues could not haue force,</l>
               <l>To aggrauate the burthen of my griefe:</l>
               <l>Th'Occaſion might moue mountaines to remorce:</l>
               <l>I hate all helpe, and hope for no releefe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 9.</head>
               <l>ALthough that words chain'd with affection faile,</l>
               <l>As that which makes me burſt abaſht t'vnfold,</l>
               <l>Yet Lines (dumbe Orators) ye may be bold,</l>
               <l>Th'inke will not bluſh, though paper doth looke pale,</l>
               <l>Ye of my ſtate the ſecrets did containe,</l>
               <l>That then through clouds of darke inuentions ſhin'd:</l>
               <l>Whilſt I diſclos'd, yet not diſclos'd my mind,</l>
               <l>Obſcure to others, but to one ore plaine.</l>
               <l>And yet that one did whiles (as th'end may proue)</l>
               <l>Not marke, not vnderſtand, or elſe deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>That (though miſterious) language of mine eyes,</l>
               <l>Which might haue bene interpreted by loue.</l>
               <l>Thus ſhe, what I diſcouered, yet conceal'd:</l>
               <l>Knowes, and not knowes; both hid, and both reueal'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Elegie</hi> 1.</head>
               <l>EVen as the dying Swan almoſt bereft of breath,</l>
               <l>Sounds dolefull notes and drearie ſongs, a preſage of her death:</l>
               <l>So ſince my date of life almoſt expir'd I find,</l>
               <l>My obſequies I ſadly ſing, as ſorrow tunes my mind,</l>
               <l>And as the rareſt Bird a pile of wood doth frame,</l>
               <l>Which being fir'd by <hi>Phoebus</hi> rayes, ſhe fals into the flame:</l>
               <l>So by two ſunnie eyes I giue my fancies fire,</l>
               <l>And burne my ſelfe with beauties raies, euen by mine owne deſire.</l>
               <l>Thus th'angry Gods atlength begin for to relent,</l>
               <l>And once to end my deathfull life, for pitie are content.</l>
               <l>For if th'infernall powers, the damned ſouls would pine,</l>
               <l>Then let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſend them to the light, to leade a life like mine.</l>
               <l>O if I could recount the croſſes and the cares,</l>
               <l>That fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my cradle to my Beare conduct me with deſpairs;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:7"/>
               <l>Then hungrie <hi>Tantalus</hi> pleas'd with his lot would ſtand:</l>
               <l>I famiſh for a ſweeter food, which ſtill is reſt my hand,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Ixions</hi> reſtleſſe wheele my fancies rowle about;</l>
               <l>And like his gueſt that ſtole heau'ns fires, they teare my bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els out.</l>
               <l>I worke an endles task and looſe my labor ſtill:</l>
               <l>Euen as the bloudie ſiſters do, that emptie as they fill,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Siſiph's</hi> ſtone returnes his guiltie ghoſt t'appall,</l>
               <l>I euer raiſe my hopes ſo high, they bruiſe me with their fall.</l>
               <l>And if I could in ſumme my ſeuerall griefes relate,</l>
               <l>All would forget their proper harms, &amp; only waile my ſtate.</l>
               <l>So grieuous is my paine, ſo painfull is my griefe,</l>
               <l>That death which doth the world affright, wold yeeld to me releefe.</l>
               <l>I haue miſhaps ſo long, as in a habit had,</l>
               <l>I thinke I looke not like my ſelfe, but when that I am ſad.</l>
               <l>As birds flie but in th'aire, fiſhes in ſeas do diue,</l>
               <l>So ſorrow is as th'Element by which I onely liue:</l>
               <l>Yet this may be admir'd as more then ſtrange in me,</l>
               <l>Although in all my Horoſcope not one cleare point I ſee.</l>
               <l>Againſt my knowledge, yet I many a time rebell,</l>
               <l>And ſeeke to gather grounds of hope, a heau'n amidſt a hell.</l>
               <l>O poyſon of the mind, that doeſt the wits bereaue:</l>
               <l>And ſhrouded with a cloke of loue doſt al the world deceiue.</l>
               <l>Thou art the rocke on which my comforts ſhip did daſh,</l>
               <l>It's thou that daily in my wounds thy hooked heades doſt waſh.</l>
               <l>Blind Tyrant it is thou by whom my hopes lye dead:</l>
               <l>That whiles throwes forth a dart of gold, &amp; whiles a lumpe of lead.</l>
               <l>Thus oft thou woundeſt two, but in two diffrent ſtates,</l>
               <l>Which through a ſtrange antipathy, th'one loues, &amp; th'other hates.</l>
               <l>O but I erre I grant, I ſhould not thee vpbraid,</l>
               <l>It's I to paſſions tyrrannie that haue my ſelfe betraid:</l>
               <l>And yet this cannot be, my iudgements aymes amiſſe:</l>
               <l>Ah deare <hi>Aurora</hi> it is thou that ruin'd haſt my bliſſe:</l>
               <l>A fault that by thy ſexe may partly be excus'd,</l>
               <l>Which ſtil doth loath what proferd is, affects what is refus'd.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:8"/>
               <l>Whilſt my diſtracted thoughts I ſtriu'd for to controule,</l>
               <l>And with fain'd geſtures did diſguiſe the anguiſh of my ſoule,</l>
               <l>Then with inuiting lookes and accents ſtampt with loue,</l>
               <l>The mask that was vpon my mind thou labordſt to remoue.</l>
               <l>And when that once enſnar'd thou in thoſe nets me ſpide,</l>
               <l>Thy ſmiles were ſhadowd with diſdaines, thy beauties clothd with pride.</l>
               <l>To reattaine thy grace I wot not how to go:</l>
               <l>Shall I once fold before thy feete, to pleade for fauour ſo?</l>
               <l>No, no, Ile proudly go my wrath for to aſſwage,</l>
               <l>And liberally at laſt enlarge the raines vnto my rage.</l>
               <l>Ile tell what we were once, our chaſt (yet feruent) loues,</l>
               <l>Whilſt in effect thou ſeem'd t'affect that which thou didſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue.</l>
               <l>Whilſt once t'engraue thy name vpon a rock I ſat,</l>
               <l>Thou vow'd to write mine in a mind, more firme by far then that:</l>
               <l>The marble ſtone once ſtampt retaines that name of thine:</l>
               <l>But ah, thy more then marble mind, it did not ſo with mine:</l>
               <l>So that which thral'd me firſt, ſhall ſet me free againe;</l>
               <l>Thoſe flames to which thy loue gaue life, ſhall die with thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine.</l>
               <l>But ah, where am I now, how is my iudgment loſt!</l>
               <l>I ſpeak as it were in my power, like one that's free to boſt:</l>
               <l>Haue I not ſold my ſelfe to be thy beauties ſlaue?</l>
               <l>And when thou tak'ſt all hope from me, thou tak'ſt but what thou gaue.</l>
               <l>That former loue of thine, did ſo poſſeſſ my mind,</l>
               <l>That for to harbor other thoughts, no roome remains behind.</l>
               <l>And th'only means by which I mind t'auenge this wrong,</l>
               <l>It is, by making of thy praiſe the burden of my ſong.</l>
               <l>Then why ſhouldſt thou ſuch ſpite for my goodwill returne?</l>
               <l>Was euer god as yet ſo mad to make his temple burne?</l>
               <l>My breſt the temple was, whence incenſe thou receiu'd,</l>
               <l>And yet thou ſet'ſt the ſame a fire, which others would haue ſau'd.</l>
               <l>But why ſhould I accuſe <hi>Aurora</hi> in this wiſe?</l>
               <l>She is as faultleſſe as ſhee's faire, as innocent as wiſe.</l>
               <l>It's but through my miſ-lucke, if any fault there be:</l>
               <l>For ſhe who was of nature mild, was cruell made by me.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:8"/>
               <l>And ſince my fortune is, in wo to be bewrapt,</l>
               <l>Ile honour her as oft before, and hate mine owne miſhap.</l>
               <l>Her rigorous courſe ſhall ſerue loyall part to proue,</l>
               <l>And as a touch-ſtone for to trie the vertue of my loue.</l>
               <l>Which when her beautie fades, ſhall be as cleare as now,</l>
               <l>My conſtancie it ſhall be known, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrinkled is her brow:</l>
               <l>So that ſuch two againe, ſhall in no age be found,</l>
               <l>She for her face, I for my faith, both worthy to be crownd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Madrig.</hi> 1.</head>
               <l>WHen in her face mine eyes I fixe,</l>
               <l>A fearefull boldneſſe takes my mind,</l>
               <l>Sweet hony loue with gall doth mixe,</l>
               <l>And is vnkindly kind:</l>
               <l>It ſeemes to breed,</l>
               <l>And is indeed</l>
               <l>A ſpeciall pleaſure to be pin'd.</l>
               <l>No danger then I dread:</l>
               <l>For though I went a thouſand times to Stix,</l>
               <l>I know ſhe can reuiue me with her eye;</l>
               <l>As many lookes, as many liues to me:</l>
               <l>And yet had I a thouſand harts,</l>
               <l>As many lookes as many darts,</l>
               <l>Might make them all to die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Seſtin.</hi> 1.</head>
               <l>HArd is my fortune, ſtormie is my ſtate,</l>
               <l>And as inconſtant as the wauing ſea,</l>
               <l>Whoſe courſe doth ſtill depend vpon the winds:</l>
               <l>For lo, my life in danger euery houre,</l>
               <l>And though euen at the point for to be loſt,</l>
               <l>Can find no comfort but a flying ſhow.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:9"/>
               <l>And yet I take ſuch pleaſure in this ſhow,</l>
               <l>That ſtill I ſtand contented with my ſtate,</l>
               <l>Although that others thinke me to be loſt:</l>
               <l>And whilſt I ſwim amidſt a dangerous ſea,</l>
               <l>Twixt feare and hope, and looking for the houre,</l>
               <l>When my laſt breath ſhould glide amongſt the winds.</l>
               <l>Lo to the ſea-man beaten with the winds,</l>
               <l>Sometimes the heau'ns a ſmiling face will ſhow,</l>
               <l>So that to reſt himſelfe he finds ſome houre.</l>
               <l>But nought (ay me) can euer calme my ſtate,</l>
               <l>Who with my teares as I would make a ſea,</l>
               <l>Am flying <hi>Silla</hi> in <hi>Charibdis</hi> loſt.</l>
               <l>The Pilote that was likely to be loſt,</l>
               <l>When he hath ſcap'd the furour of the winds,</l>
               <l>Doth ſtraight forget the dangers of the ſea.</l>
               <l>But I vnhappie I, can neuer ſhow,</l>
               <l>No kind of token of a quiet ſtate,</l>
               <l>And am tormented ſtill from houre to houre.</l>
               <l>O ſhall I neuer ſee that happie houre,</l>
               <l>When I (whoſe hopes once vtterly were loſt)</l>
               <l>May find a meanes to re-erect my ſtate,</l>
               <l>And leaue for to breath foorth ſuch dolorous winds,</l>
               <l>Whilſt I my ſelfe in conſtancie do ſhow</l>
               <l>A rocke againſt the waues amidſt the ſea.</l>
               <l>As many waters make in end a ſea,</l>
               <l>As many minutes make in end an houre:</l>
               <l>And ſtill what went before th'effect doth ſhow:</l>
               <l>So all the labours that I long haue loſt,</l>
               <l>As one that was but wreſtling with the winds,</l>
               <l>May once in end concurre to bleſſe my ſtate.</l>
               <l>And once my ſtorme-ſtead ſtate ſau'd from the ſea,</l>
               <l>In ſpite of aduerſe winds, may in one houre</l>
               <l>Pay all my labors loſt, at leaſt in ſhow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Song</hi> 2.</head>
               <l>WHil'ſt I by wailing ſought</l>
               <l>T'haue in ſome ſort aſſwag'd my griefe,</l>
               <l>I found that rage gaue no reliefe,</l>
               <l>And carefulneſſe did but increaſe my feares:</l>
               <l>Then now Ile mourne for nought,</l>
               <l>But in my ſecret thought,</l>
               <l>Will theſaurize all my miſchiefe.</l>
               <l>For long experienc'd wo well witneſſe beares,</l>
               <l>That teares cannot quench ſighes, nor ſighs drie teares.</l>
               <l>To calme a ſtormie brow,</l>
               <l>The world doth know how I did ſmart,</l>
               <l>Yet could not moue that marble hart,</l>
               <l>Which was too much to crueltie inclin'd:</l>
               <l>But to her rigour now,</l>
               <l>I lift my hands and bow,</l>
               <l>And in her grace will claime no part:</l>
               <l>I take great paines of purpoſe to be pin'd,</l>
               <l>And onely mourne to ſatisfie my mind.</l>
               <l>How I my dayes haue ſpent,</l>
               <l>The heau'ns aboue no doubt they know;</l>
               <l>The world hath likewiſe ſeene below,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt with my ſighes I poyſon'd al the ayre:</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſtreames which I augment,</l>
               <l>Thoſe woods where I lament,</l>
               <l>I thinke my ſtate could clearely ſhow:</l>
               <l>By thoſe the ſame reſts regiſtred as rare,</l>
               <l>That ſuch like monſtrous things vs'd to declare.</l>
               <l>The trees where I did bide,</l>
               <l>Seem'd for to chide my froward fate:</l>
               <l>Then whiſling wail'd my wretched ſtate,</l>
               <l>And bowing whiles to heare my wofull ſong:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:10"/>
               <l>They ſpred their branches wide,</l>
               <l>Of purpoſe me to hide:</l>
               <l>Then of their leaues did make my ſeate:</l>
               <l>And if they reaſon had as they are ſtrong,</l>
               <l>No doubt but they would ioyne t'auenge my wrong.</l>
               <l>The beaſts in euery glen,</l>
               <l>Which firſt to kill me had ordain'd,</l>
               <l>Were by my priuiledge reſtrain'd,</l>
               <l>Who indenized was within thoſe bounds:</l>
               <l>I harbor'd in a den,</l>
               <l>I fled the ſight of men,</l>
               <l>No ſigne of reaſon I retain'd.</l>
               <l>The beaſts they flie not when the hunter ſounds,</l>
               <l>As I at mine owne thoughts when <hi>Cupid</hi> hounds.</l>
               <l>This moues me, my diſtreſſe</l>
               <l>And ſorrowes ſometime to conceale,</l>
               <l>Leſt that the torments which I feele,</l>
               <l>Might likewiſe my concitizens annoy.</l>
               <l>And partly I confeſſe,</l>
               <l>Becauſe the meanes grow leſſe</l>
               <l>By which I ſhould ſuch harmes reueale:</l>
               <l>Which I proteſt, doth but preiudge my ioy,</l>
               <l>That ſtill do ſtriue my ſelfe for to deſtroy.</l>
               <l>All comfort I deſpight,</l>
               <l>And willingly with wo comport,</l>
               <l>My paſſions do appeare a ſport;</l>
               <l>I take a ſpeciall pleaſure to complaine:</l>
               <l>All things that moue delight,</l>
               <l>I with diſdaine acquite.</l>
               <l>Small eaſe ſeemes much, long trauels ſhort,</l>
               <l>A world of pleaſure is not worth my paine,</l>
               <l>I will not change my loſſe with others gaine.</l>
               <l>Here rob'd of all repoſe,</l>
               <l>Not interrupted by repaire,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:10"/>
               <l>My fancies freely I declare:</l>
               <l>And counting all my croſſes one by one,</l>
               <l>I daily do diſcloſe</l>
               <l>To woods and vales my woes.</l>
               <l>And as I ſaw <hi>Aurora</hi> there,</l>
               <l>I thinke to her that I my ſtate bemone,</l>
               <l>When in effect it is but to a ſtone.</l>
               <l>This my moſt monſtrous ill,</l>
               <l>Compaſſion moues in euery thing:</l>
               <l>When as I ſhout the forreſts ring;</l>
               <l>When I begin to grone, the beaſts they bray:</l>
               <l>The trees they teares diſtill,</l>
               <l>The riuers all ſtand ſtill,</l>
               <l>The birds my Tragedie they ſing;</l>
               <l>The wofull Eccho waites vpon my way,</l>
               <l>Prompt to reſound my accents when I ſtay.</l>
               <l>When wearied I remaine,</l>
               <l>That ſighs, teares, voice, and all do faile,</l>
               <l>Diſcolour'd, bloudleſſe, and growne pale,</l>
               <l>Vpon the earth my bodie I diſtend:</l>
               <l>And then orecome with paine,</l>
               <l>I agonize againe:</l>
               <l>And paſſions do ſo farre preuaile,</l>
               <l>That though I want the meanes my woes to ſpend,</l>
               <l>A mournfull meaning neuer hath an end.</l>
               <l>My child in deſerts borne,</l>
               <l>For griefe-tun'd eares thy accents frame,</l>
               <l>And tell to thoſe thy plaints that ſcorne,</l>
               <l>Thou plead'ſt for pitie, not for fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 10.</head>
               <l>I Sweare <hi>Aurora,</hi> by thy ſtarrie eyes,</l>
               <l>And by thoſe golden lockes whoſe locke none ſlips,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:11"/>
               <l>And by the Corall of thy roſie lippes,</l>
               <l>And by the naked ſnowes which beautie dies,</l>
               <l>I ſweare by all the iewels of thy mind,</l>
               <l>Whoſe like yet neuer worldly treaſure bought,</l>
               <l>Thy ſolide iudgement and thy generous thought,</l>
               <l>Which in this darkened age haue clearely ſhin'd:</l>
               <l>I ſweare by thoſe, and by my ſpotleſſe loue,</l>
               <l>And by my ſecret, yet moſt feruent fires,</l>
               <l>That I haue neuer nurc'd but chaſt deſires,</l>
               <l>And ſuch as modeſtie might well approue.</l>
               <l>Then ſince I loue thoſe vertuous parts in thee,</l>
               <l>Shouldſt thou not loue this vertuous mind in me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 11.</head>
               <l>AH that it was my fortune to be borne,</l>
               <l>Now in the time of this degener'd age,</l>
               <l>When ſome, in whom impietie doth rage,</l>
               <l>Do all the reſt diſcredit whilſt they ſcorne.</l>
               <l>And this is growne to ſuch a cuſtome now,</l>
               <l>That thoſe are thought to haue the braueſt ſpirits,</l>
               <l>Who can faine fancies and imagine merits:</l>
               <l>As who but for their luſts of loue allow.</l>
               <l>And yet in this I had good hap, I find,</l>
               <l>That chanc'd to chaine my thoughts to ſuch an one,</l>
               <l>Whoſe iudgement is ſo cleare, that ſhe anone</l>
               <l>Can by the outward geſtures iudge the mind.</l>
               <l>Yet wit and fortune rarely waite on one,</l>
               <l>She knowes the beſt, yet can make choice of none.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 12.</head>
               <l>SWeet bluſhing goddeſſe of the golden morning,</l>
               <l>Faire patroneſſe of all the worlds affaires,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:11"/>
               <l>Thou art become ſo careleſſe of my cares,</l>
               <l>That I muſt name thee goddeſſe of my mourning.</l>
               <l>Lo how the Sunne part of thy burthen beares,</l>
               <l>And whileſt thou doeſt in pearly drops regrate,</l>
               <l>As t'were to pitie thy diſtreſſed ſtate,</l>
               <l>Exhales the Chriſtall of thy gliſtring teares;</l>
               <l>But I poure forth my vowes before thy ſhrine,</l>
               <l>And whilſt thou doſt my louing zeale deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>Do drowne my heart in th'ocean of mine eyes;</l>
               <l>Yet daign'ſt thou not to drie theſe teares of mine,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe it be with th'<hi>Aetna</hi> of deſires,</l>
               <l>Which euen amidſt thoſe floods doth foſter fires.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 13.</head>
               <l>LO how that Time doth ſtill diſturbe my peace,</l>
               <l>And hath his courſe to my confuſion bent;</l>
               <l>For when th'Occaſion kindly giues conſent,</l>
               <l>That I ſhould feed vpon <hi>Auroraes</hi> face:</l>
               <l>Then mounted on the chariot of the Sunne,</l>
               <l>That tyrant Time doth poſt ſo faſt away,</l>
               <l>That whilſt I but aduiſe what I ſhould ſay,</l>
               <l>I'm forc'd to end ere I haue well begun:</l>
               <l>And then againe it doth ſo ſlowly flie,</l>
               <l>Whilſt I leaue her whom I hold onely deare,</l>
               <l>Each minute makes an houre, each houre a yeare,</l>
               <l>Yeares luſters ſeeme, one luſter ten to me.</l>
               <l>Thus changing courſe to change my ſtate I know,</l>
               <l>In preſence time proues ſwift, in abſence ſlow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 14.</head>
               <l>WHen firſt I view'd that ey-enchanting face,</l>
               <l>Which for the world chiefe treaſure was eſteem'd,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:12"/>
               <l>I iudging ſimply all things as they ſeem'd,</l>
               <l>Thought humble lookes had promiſt pitie place;</l>
               <l>Yet were they but ambuſhments, to deceiue</l>
               <l>My ouer-raſh heart that fear'd no ſecret fires:</l>
               <l>Thy baſhfulneſſe emboldned my deſires,</l>
               <l>Which ſeem'd to offer what I was to craue.</l>
               <l>Can crueltie then borrow beauties ſhape?</l>
               <l>And pride ſo decke it ſelfe with modeſt lookes?</l>
               <l>Too pleaſant baites to hide ſuch poiſon'd hookes,</l>
               <l>Whoſe vnſuſpected ſlight none can eſcape.</l>
               <l>VVho can eſcape this more then diuelliſh art,</l>
               <l>VVhen golden haires diſguiſe a brazen heart?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 15.</head>
               <l>STay blubring pen to ſpot one that's ſo pure;</l>
               <l>She is my loue, although ſhe be vnkind,</l>
               <l>I muſt admire that diamantine mind,</l>
               <l>And praiſe thoſe eyes that do my death procure:</l>
               <l>Nor will I willingly thoſe thoughts endure,</l>
               <l>That are to ſuch apoſtaſie inclin'd.</l>
               <l>Shall ſhe, euen ſhe in whom all vertue ſhin'd,</l>
               <l>Be wrong'd by me? ſhall I her worth iniure?</l>
               <l>No, rather let me die, and die diſdain'd,</l>
               <l>Long ere I thinke, much leſſe I ſpeake the thing,</l>
               <l>That may diſgrace vnto her beautie bring,</l>
               <l>VVho ore my fancies hath ſo ſweetly raign'd.</l>
               <l>If any pitying me will damne her part,</l>
               <l>I'le make th'amends, and for her error ſmart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 16.</head>
               <l>LOue ſo engag'd my fancies to that faire,</l>
               <l>That whilſt I liue I ſhall aduance her name,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:12"/>
               <l>And imping ſtately fethers in her fame,</l>
               <l>May make it glide more glorious through the aire:</l>
               <l>So ſhe in beauties right ſhall haue her ſhare,</l>
               <l>And I who ſtriue her praiſes to proclaime,</l>
               <l>Encourag'd with ſo excellent a theame,</l>
               <l>May reſt inrold amongſt thoſe that were rare.</l>
               <l>O if my wit were equall with her worth!</l>
               <l>Th'<hi>Antipodes</hi> all rauiſh'd by report,</l>
               <l>From regions moſt remou'd ſhould here reſort,</l>
               <l>To gaze vpon the face which I ſet forth:</l>
               <l>Or were my wit but equall with my will,</l>
               <l>I with her praiſe both <hi>Titans</hi> bow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s ſhould fill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 17.</head>
               <l>I Saw ſixe gallant Nymphes, I ſaw but one,</l>
               <l>One ſtain'd them all, one did them onely grace;</l>
               <l>And with the ſhining of her beauteous face,</l>
               <l>Gaue to the world new light when it had none.</l>
               <l>Then when the god that guides the light was gone,</l>
               <l>And ore the hils directed had his race,</l>
               <l>A brighter farre then he ſupplide his place,</l>
               <l>And lightned our horizon here anone.</l>
               <l>The reſt pale Moones were bettered by this Sunne,</l>
               <l>They borrowed beames from her ſtar-ſtaining eyes:</l>
               <l>Still when ſhe ſets her lights, their ſhining dies,</l>
               <l>And at their opening is againe begun:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phoebus</hi> all day I would be bard thy light,</l>
               <l>For to be ſhin'd on by this Sunne at night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 18.</head>
               <l>PRaiſe-worthy part where praiſes praiſe is plac'd,</l>
               <l>As th'Oracle of th'Earth beleeu'd below.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:13"/>
               <l>Ile to the world thy beauties wonders ſhow,</l>
               <l>O vnſtain'd Roſe, with Lillies interlac'd:</l>
               <l>But what a labour hath my Muſe imbrac'd?</l>
               <l>Shall I commend the corall, or the ſnow,</l>
               <l>Which ſuch a ſweet embalmed breath did blow,</l>
               <l>That th'orientall odours are diſgrac'd?</l>
               <l>Mouth moiſtned with celeſtiall Nectar ſtill,</l>
               <l>Whoſe muſicke oft my famiſh'd eares hath fed,</l>
               <l>With ſoftned ſounds in ſugred ſpeeches ſpred,</l>
               <l>Whilſt pearles and rubies did vnfold thy will.</l>
               <l>I wiſh that thy laſt kiſſe might ſtop my breath,</l>
               <l>Then I would thinke I died a happie death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 19.</head>
               <l>LEt ſome bewitch'd with a deceitfull ſhow,</l>
               <l>Loue earthly things vnworthily eſteem'd;</l>
               <l>And loſing that which cannot be redeem'd,</l>
               <l>Pay backe with paine according as they ow:</l>
               <l>But I diſdaine to caſt mine eyes ſo low,</l>
               <l>That for my thoughts ouer baſe a ſubiect ſeem'd,</l>
               <l>Which ſtill the vulgar courſe too beaten deem'd;</l>
               <l>And loftier things delighted for to know,</l>
               <l>Though preſently this plague me but with paine,</l>
               <l>And vexe the world with wondering at my woes:</l>
               <l>Yet hauing gain'd that long deſir'd repoſe,</l>
               <l>My mirth may more miraculous remaine.</l>
               <l>That for the which long languiſhing I pine,</l>
               <l>It is a ſhow, but yet a ſhow diuine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Song</hi> 3.</head>
               <l>WHen as my fancies firſt began to flie,</l>
               <l>Which youth had but englar'd of late,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:13"/>
               <l>Enamour'd of mine owne conceit,</l>
               <l>I ſported with my thoughts that then were free;</l>
               <l>And neuer thought to ſee</l>
               <l>No ſuch miſhap at all,</l>
               <l>As might haue made them thrall.</l>
               <l>VVhen lo, euen then my fate</l>
               <l>Was laboring to orethrow my proſprous ſtate:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Cupid</hi> did conſpire my fall,</l>
               <l>And with my honie mixt his gall,</l>
               <l>Long ere I thought that ſuch a thing could be.</l>
               <l>Loue after many ſtratagems were tride,</l>
               <l>His griefe t'his mother did impart,</l>
               <l>And praid her to find out ſome art,</l>
               <l>By which he might haue meanes t'abate my pride.</l>
               <l>And ſhe by chance eſpide</l>
               <l>VVhere beauties beautie ſtraid,</l>
               <l>Like whom ſtraight wayes arraid,</l>
               <l>She tooke a powerfull dart,</l>
               <l>VVhich had the force t'nflame an icie hart:</l>
               <l>And when ſhe had this ſlight aſſaid,</l>
               <l>The time no longer ſhe delaid,</l>
               <l>But made an arrow through my bowels glide.</l>
               <l>Then when I had receiu'd the deadly wound,</l>
               <l>And that the goddeſſe fled my ſight,</l>
               <l>Inueigled with her beauties light:</l>
               <l>Firſt hauing followed ore the ſtable ground,</l>
               <l>Vnto the deepe profound,</l>
               <l>My courſe I next did hold,</l>
               <l>In hope the truth t'vnfold.</l>
               <l>If <hi>Thetis</hi> by her might,</l>
               <l>Or ſome ſea-nimph had vs'd the fatall ſlight:</l>
               <l>In th'Hauen I did a barke behold,</l>
               <l>VVith ſailes of ſilke, and oares of gold,</l>
               <l>VVhich being richly deckt, did ſeeme moſt ſound,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:14"/>
               <l>In this imbark'd when from the port I paſt,</l>
               <l>Faire gales at firſt my ſailes did greete,</l>
               <l>And all ſeem'd for the voyage meete;</l>
               <l>But yet I ſail'd not long, when lo a blaſt</l>
               <l>Did quite oreturne my maſt;</l>
               <l>Which being once throwne downe,</l>
               <l>Still looking for to drowne,</l>
               <l>And ſtriken off my feete,</l>
               <l>Betwixt two rockes I did with danger fleete:</l>
               <l>Whilſt ſeas their waues with clouds did crowne,</l>
               <l>Yet with much toile I got a towne,</l>
               <l>Whereas I ſaw her whom I ſought at laſt.</l>
               <l>What were my ioyes then ſcarcely can be thought;</l>
               <l>When in diſtreſſe ſhe did me ſpie,</l>
               <l>My mind with fortunes beſt to trie,</l>
               <l>She to a chamber made of pearle me brought,</l>
               <l>Where whilſt I proudly ſought,</l>
               <l>In ſtate with <hi>Ioue</hi> to ſtriue;</l>
               <l>A flame which did arriue</l>
               <l>In twinckling of an eye,</l>
               <l>The chamber burn'd, and left me like to die:</l>
               <l>For after that, how could I liue,</l>
               <l>That in the depth of woes did diue,</l>
               <l>To ſee my glorie to confuſion brought?</l>
               <l>But with proſperitie yet once againe,</l>
               <l>(To trie what was within my mind)</l>
               <l>She on my backe two wings did bind,</l>
               <l>Like to <hi>Ioues</hi> birds, and I who did diſdaine</l>
               <l>On th'earth for to remaine,</l>
               <l>Since I might ſoare ore all,</l>
               <l>Did th'airie ſprites appall,</l>
               <l>Till through fierce flying blind,</l>
               <l>I was encountred with a mightie wind,</l>
               <l>With which through th'aire toſs'd like a ball,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:14"/>
               <l>Euen as a ſtarre from heauen doth fall,</l>
               <l>I glided to the ground almoſt quite ſlaine.</l>
               <l>Then (as it ſeem'd) growne kinder then before,</l>
               <l>This Ladie for to cure my wounds,</l>
               <l>Did ſeeke ore all the neareſt bounds,</l>
               <l>To trie what might my wonted ſtate reſtore,</l>
               <l>And ſtill her care grew more;</l>
               <l>Of flowers ſhe made my bed,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Nectar</hi> I was fed,</l>
               <l>And with moſt ſurged ſounds,</l>
               <l>Oft luld aſleepe betwixt two yuorie rounds,</l>
               <l>Whoſe daintie turrets all were cled</l>
               <l>With Lillies white, and Roſes red,</l>
               <l>The leaues of which could onely eaſe my ſore.</l>
               <l>When I was cur'd of euery thing ſaue care,</l>
               <l>She whom I name (without a name)</l>
               <l>Did leade me forth t'a mightie frame,</l>
               <l>A curious building that was wondrous faire,</l>
               <l>A labyrinth moſt rare,</l>
               <l>All made of precious ſtones:</l>
               <l>That which in Candie once</l>
               <l>Did hide <hi>Paſiphaes</hi> ſhame,</l>
               <l>Was not ſo large, though more enlarg'd by fame:</l>
               <l>There whilſt none liſtned to their mones,</l>
               <l>A world of men ſhed weightie grones,</l>
               <l>That tortur'd were with th'engines of deſpaire.</l>
               <l>As <hi>Forth</hi> at <hi>Sterling,</hi> glides at t'were in doubt,</l>
               <l>What way ſhe ſhould direct her courſe;</l>
               <l>If to the ſea, or to the ſource,</l>
               <l>And ſporting with her ſelfe, her ſelfe doth flout:</l>
               <l>So wandred I about</l>
               <l>In th'intricated way,</l>
               <l>Where whilſt I did ſtill ſtray,</l>
               <l>With an abrupt diſcourſe,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:15"/>
               <l>And with a courteſie, I muſt ſay courſe,</l>
               <l>My beauteous guide fled quite away,</l>
               <l>And would not do ſo much as ſtay,</l>
               <l>To lend me firſt a thread to leade me out:</l>
               <l>Through many a corner whilſt I ſtaggring went,</l>
               <l>VVhich in the darke I did embrace,</l>
               <l>A nymph like th'other in the face,</l>
               <l>But whoſe affections were more mildly bent,</l>
               <l>Spying my breath neare ſpent,</l>
               <l>Plaid <hi>Ariadnes</hi> part,</l>
               <l>And led me by the heart</l>
               <l>Out of the guilefull place.</l>
               <l>And like th'vngratefull <hi>Theſeus</hi> in this caſe,</l>
               <l>I made not my deliuerer ſmart:</l>
               <l>Thus oft affraid my panting hart,</l>
               <l>Can yet ſcarce truſt t'haue ſcap'd ſome bad euent.</l>
               <l>If any muſe miſterious ſong,</l>
               <l>At thoſe ſtrange things that thou haſt ſhowne,</l>
               <l>And wot not what to deeme;</l>
               <l>Tell that they do me wrong,</l>
               <l>I am my ſelfe, what ere I ſeeme,</l>
               <l>And muſt go mask'd, that I may not be knowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 20.</head>
               <l>VNhappie ghoſt go waile thy griefe below,</l>
               <l>VVhere neuer ſoule but endleſſe horror ſees,</l>
               <l>Diſmaske thy mind amongſt the mirtle trees,</l>
               <l>Which here I ſee thou art aſham'd to ſhow;</l>
               <l>This breaſt that ſuch a fierie breath doth blow,</l>
               <l>Muſt haue of force ſome flood thoſe flames to freeze.</l>
               <l>And ô that drowſie <hi>Lethe</hi> beſt agrees,</l>
               <l>To quench theſe euils that come, becauſe I know</l>
               <l>Since ſhe whom I haue harbour'd in my heart,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:15"/>
               <l>Will grant me now no portion of her mind,</l>
               <l>I die content, becauſe ſhe liues vnkind,</l>
               <l>And ſuffers one whom once ſhe grac'd to ſmart:</l>
               <l>But I lament that I haue liu'd ſo long,</l>
               <l>Leſt blaming her, I ere I die do wrong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 21.</head>
               <l>IN this curſt breſt, borne onely to be pin'd,</l>
               <l>Some furie hath ſuch fantaſies infus'd,</l>
               <l>That I though with her cruelties well vs'd,</l>
               <l>Can daigne my ſelfe to ſerue one ſo inclind.</l>
               <l>Such helliſh horrors toſſe my reſtleſſe mind,</l>
               <l>That with beguiling hopes vainely abus'd,</l>
               <l>It yet affects that which the Fates refus'd,</l>
               <l>And dare preſume to pleade for that vnkind:</l>
               <l>Then traiterous thoughts, that haue ſeduc'd my ſence,</l>
               <l>Whoſe vaine inuentions I haue oft times wail'd,</l>
               <l>I baniſh you the bounds, whereas ye fail'd</l>
               <l>To liue from hence, exil'd for your offence.</l>
               <l>But what auailes all this, though I would leaue them,</l>
               <l>If that the heart they hurt againe receiue them?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 22.</head>
               <l>WHilſt nothing could my fancies courſe controule,</l>
               <l>T'haue matchleſſe beauties match'd with matchles loue,</l>
               <l>And from thy mind all rigor to remoue,</l>
               <l>I ſacrific'd th'affections of my ſoule:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Hercules</hi> had neuer greater paines,</l>
               <l>With dangerous toiles his ſtep-dames wrath t'aſſwage,</l>
               <l>Then I, while as I did my thoughts engage,</l>
               <l>With my deſerts t'oreballance thy diſdaines:</l>
               <l>Yet all my merits could not moue thy mind,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:16"/>
               <l>But furniſh'd trophees for t'adorne thy pride,</l>
               <l>That in the fornace of thoſe troubles tride</l>
               <l>The temper of my loue, whoſe flame I find</l>
               <l>Fin'd and refin'd too oft, but faintles flaſhes,</l>
               <l>And muſt within ſhort time fall downe in aſhes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 23.</head>
               <l>EArſt ſtately <hi>Iuno</hi> in agreat diſdaine,</l>
               <l>Her beautie by ones iudgement but iniur'd,</l>
               <l>T'auenge on a whole nation oft procur'd,</l>
               <l>And for ones fault ſaw many thouſands ſlaine:</l>
               <l>But ſhe whom I would to the world preferre,</l>
               <l>Although I ſpend my ſp'rit to praiſe her name,</l>
               <l>She in a rage, as if I ſought her ſhame,</l>
               <l>Thirſts for my bloud, and ſaith I wrong her farre.</l>
               <l>Thus ruthleſſe tyrants that are bent to kill,</l>
               <l>Of all occaſions procreate a cauſe:</l>
               <l>How can ſhe hate me now (this makes me pauſe)</l>
               <l>When yet I cannot but commend her ſtill?</l>
               <l>For this her fault comes of a modeſt mind,</l>
               <l>Where fond ambition made the goddeſſe blind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sonet</hi> 24.</head>
               <l>A Countrie Swaine while as he lay at reſt,</l>
               <l>Neare dead for cold a ſerpent did perceiue,</l>
               <l>And through prepoſterous pitie ſtraight would ſaue</l>
               <l>That vipers life, whoſe death had bene his beſt:</l>
               <l>For being by his boſomes heate reuiu'd,</l>
               <l>O vile ingratitude! a monſtrous thing,</l>
               <l>Not thinking how he ſtrengthned had her ſting,</l>
               <l>She kild the courteous Clowne by whom ſhe liu'd.</l>
               <l>I in this maner harbour'd in my hart</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:16"/>
               <l>A ſpeechleſſe picture, deſtitute of force,</l>
               <l>And lo attracted with a vaine remorce,</l>
               <l>I gaue it life, and foſtred it with art;</l>
               <l>But like that poiſnous viper being ſtrong,</l>
               <l>She burn'd the breſt where ſhe had lodg'd ſo long.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 25.</head>
               <l>CLeare mouing criſtall, pure as the Sunne beames,</l>
               <l>Which had the honor for to be the glaſſe,</l>
               <l>Of the moſt daintie beautie euer was;</l>
               <l>And with her ſhadow did inrich thy ſtreames,</l>
               <l>Thy treaſures now cannot be bought for monie,</l>
               <l>Whilſt ſhe dranke thee, thou drank'ſt thy fill of loue,</l>
               <l>And of thoſe roſes didſt the ſweetnes proue,</l>
               <l>From which the Bees of loue do gather honie:</l>
               <l>Th'ambroſian liquor that he fils aboue,</l>
               <l>Whom th'Eagle rauiſh'd from th'inferior round,</l>
               <l>It is not like this Nectar (though renown'd)</l>
               <l>Which thou didſt taſt, whilſt ſhe her lips did moue:</l>
               <l>But yet beware leſt burning with deſires,</l>
               <l>That all thy waters cannot quench thy fires.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 26.</head>
               <l>ILe giue thee leaue my loue, in beauties field</l>
               <l>To reare red colours whiles, and bend thine eyes;</l>
               <l>Thoſe that are baſhfull ſtill, I quite deſpiſe</l>
               <l>Such ſimple ſoules are too ſoone mou'd to yeeld:</l>
               <l>Let maieſtie arm'd in thy count'nance ſit,</l>
               <l>As that which will no iniurie receiue;</l>
               <l>And Ile not hate thee, whiles although thou haue</l>
               <l>A ſparke of pride, ſo it be rul'd by wit.</l>
               <l>This is to chaſtitie a powerfull guard,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:17"/>
               <l>VVhilſt haughtie thoughts all ſeruile things eſchue,</l>
               <l>That ſparke hath power the paſſions to ſubdue,</l>
               <l>And would of glorie chalenge a reward:</l>
               <l>But do not fall in loue with thine owne ſelfe;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Narciſſus</hi> earſt was loſt on ſuch a ſhelfe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 27.</head>
               <l>THe thoughts of thoſe I cannot but diſproue,</l>
               <l>VVho baſely loſt their thraldome muſt bemone:</l>
               <l>I ſcorne to yeeld my ſelfe to ſuch a one,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe birth and virtue is not worth my loue.</l>
               <l>No, ſince it is my fortune to be thrall,</l>
               <l>I muſt be fettred with a golden band;</l>
               <l>And if I die, ile die by <hi>Hectors</hi> hand:</l>
               <l>So may the victors fame excuſe my fall;</l>
               <l>And if by any meanes I muſt be blind,</l>
               <l>Then it ſhall be by gazing on the Sunne;</l>
               <l>Oft by thoſe meanes the greateſt haue bene wonne,</l>
               <l>Who muſt like beſt of ſuch a generous mind:</l>
               <l>At leaſt by this I haue allow'd of fame,</l>
               <l>Much honour if I winne, if loſe, no ſhame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 28.</head>
               <l>THen whilſt that <hi>Lathmos</hi> did containe her bliſſe,</l>
               <l>Chaſt <hi>Phoebe</hi> left her Church ſo much admir'd,</l>
               <l>And when her brother from that bounds retir'd,</l>
               <l>Would of the ſleepie ſhepheard ſteale a kiſſe,</l>
               <l>But to no greater grace I craue to clime,</l>
               <l>Then of my goddeſſe whiles whilſt ſhe repoſes,</l>
               <l>That I might kiſſe the ſtil-ſelfekiſſing roſes,</l>
               <l>And ſteale of her that which was ſtolne of him;</l>
               <l>And though I know that this would onely proue,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:17"/>
               <l>A maim'd delight, whereof th'one halfe would want,</l>
               <l>Yet whil'ſt the light did <hi>Morpheus</hi> power ſupplant:</l>
               <l>If that my theft did her diſpleaſure moue,</l>
               <l>I render would all that I rob'd againe,</l>
               <l>And for each kiſſe I take would giue her twaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 29.</head>
               <l>I Enuie not <hi>Endimion</hi> now no more,</l>
               <l>Nor all the happineſſe his ſleepe did yeeld,</l>
               <l>While as <hi>Diana</hi> ſtraying through the field,</l>
               <l>Suck'd from his ſleep-ſeal'd lippes balme for her ſore:</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt I embrac'd the ſhadow of my death,</l>
               <l>I dreaming did farre greater pleaſure proue,</l>
               <l>And quaff'd with <hi>Cupid</hi> ſugred draughts of loue,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Ioue</hi>-like feeding on a Nectar'd breath:</l>
               <l>Now iudge which of vs two might be moſt prowd;</l>
               <l>He got a kiſſe yet not enioy'd it right,</l>
               <l>And I got none, yet taſted that delight</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Venus</hi> on <hi>Adonis</hi> once beſtow'd:</l>
               <l>He onely got the bodie of a kiſſe,</l>
               <l>And I the ſoule of it, which he did miſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 30.</head>
               <l>ASpiring Sprite, flie low, yet flie deſpaire,</l>
               <l>Thy haughtie thoughts the heau'nly powers deſpiſe.</l>
               <l>Thus ballanc'd lo betwixt the earth and th'aire,</l>
               <l>I wot not whether for to fall or riſe;</l>
               <l>Through deſperate dangers whiles I ſcale the skies,</l>
               <l>As if that nought my courage could reſtraine,</l>
               <l>When lo, anon downe in the Center lies</l>
               <l>That reſtleſſe mind, which th'heau'ns did once containe;</l>
               <l>I toyle for that which I cannot attaine:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:18"/>
               <l>Yet fortune nought but fickleneſſe affoords:</l>
               <l>Where I haue bene, I hope to be againe;</l>
               <l>She once muſt change, her common courſe records.</l>
               <l>Although my hap be hard, my heart is hie,</l>
               <l>And it muſt mount, or elſe my bodie die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Elegie</hi> 2.</head>
               <l>LEt not the world beleeue th'accuſing of my fate</l>
               <l>Tends to allure it to condole with me my tragick ſtate:</l>
               <l>Nor that I haue ſent foorth theſe ſtormie teares of rage,</l>
               <l>So by disburd'ning of my breſt, my ſorrowes to aſſwage.</l>
               <l>No, no, that ſerues for nought, I craue no ſuch reliefe,</l>
               <l>Nor will I yeeld that any ſhould be partners of my griefe.</l>
               <l>My fantaſie to feed I only ſpend thoſe teares:</l>
               <l>My plaints pleaſe me, no muſicke ſounds ſo ſweetly in my eares,</l>
               <l>I wiſh that from my birth I had acquainted bene</l>
               <l>Still with miſhaps, and neuer had but woes and horrors ſeene:</l>
               <l>Then ignorant of Ioyes, lamenting as I do,</l>
               <l>As thinking all men did the like, I might content me too.</l>
               <l>But ah, my fate was worſe: for it (as in a glaſſe)</l>
               <l>Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w'd me through litle blinkes of bliſſe, the ſtare wherin I was.</l>
               <l>Which vnperfected ioyes, ſcarce conſtant for an houre,</l>
               <l>Were like but to a watrie Sunne, that ſhines before a ſhoure.</l>
               <l>For if I euer thought or rather dream'd of Ioyes,</l>
               <l>That litle lightning but foreſhew'd a thunder of annoyes:</l>
               <l>It was but like the fruit that <hi>Tantalus</hi> torments,</l>
               <l>Which while he ſees &amp; nought attains, his hunger but augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</l>
               <l>For ſo the ſhadow of that but imagin'd mirth,</l>
               <l>Cal'd all the croſſes to record, I ſuffer'd ſince my birth,</l>
               <l>Which are to be bewail'd, but hard to be redreſt:</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſtrange effects may well be felt, but cannot be expreſt.</l>
               <l>Iudge what the feeling was, when thinking on things paſt,</l>
               <l>I tremble at the torment yet, and ſtand a time agaſt.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:18"/>
               <l>Yet do I not repent, but will with patience pine:</l>
               <l>For though I mourne, I murmure not, like men that do repine.</l>
               <l>I graunt I waile my lot, yet I approue her will;</l>
               <l>What my ſoules oracle thinkes good, I neuer ſhall thinke ill.</l>
               <l>If I had onely ſought a ſalue to eaſe my paines,</l>
               <l>Long ſince I had bewail'd my lot alongſt th'<hi>Elyſian</hi> plaines:</l>
               <l>Yet mind I not in this ſelfe-louer-like to die,</l>
               <l>As one that car'd not for her loſſe, ſo I my ſelfe were free.</l>
               <l>No, may ten nights annoyes make her one night ſecure,</l>
               <l>A day of dolors vnto her a moments mirth procure:</l>
               <l>Or may a yeares laments reioyce her halfe an houre,</l>
               <l>May ſeuen years ſorrows make her glad, I ſhal not think the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoure,</l>
               <l>And if ſhe do delight to heare of my diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>Then ô bleſt I, who ſo may haue th'occaſion her to pleaſe:</l>
               <l>For now the cauſe I liue, is not for loue of life,</l>
               <l>But onely for to honour her that holds me in this ſtrife.</l>
               <l>And ere thoſe vowes I make do vnperform'd eſcape,</l>
               <l>This world ſhal once againe renuerſt reſume her ſhapeleſſe ſhape.</l>
               <l>But what? what haue I vow'd, my paſſions were too ſtrong,</l>
               <l>As if the mildeſt of the world delighted to do wrong:</l>
               <l>As ſhe whom I adore with ſo deuote a mind,</l>
               <l>Could reſt content to ſee me ſtarue, be glad to ſee me pin'd.</l>
               <l>No, no, ſhe wailes my ſtate, and would appeaſe my cares,</l>
               <l>Yet interdited to the fates, conformes her will to theirs.</l>
               <l>Then ô vnhappie man, whom euen thy Saint would ſaue,</l>
               <l>And yet thy cruell deſtinie doth damne thee to the graue.</l>
               <l>This ſentence then may ſerue for to confound my feares,</l>
               <l>Why burſt I not my breſt with ſighs, &amp; drowne mine eyes with tears?</l>
               <l>Ah, I haue mourn'd ſo much, that I may mourn no more,</l>
               <l>My miſeries paſſe numbring now, plaints periſh in their ſtore.</l>
               <l>The meanes t'vnlode my breſt doth quite begin to faile;</l>
               <l>For being drunke with too much dole, I wot not how to waile.</l>
               <l>And ſince I want a way my anguiſh to reueale,</l>
               <l>Of force contented with my Fate, Ile ſuffer and conceale.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:19"/>
               <l>And for to vſe the world, euen as my loue vs'd me.</l>
               <l>Ile vſe a count'nance like to one, whoſe mind fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grief were free.</l>
               <l>For when ſhe did diſdaine, ſhe ſhew'd a ſmiling face,</l>
               <l>Euen then when ſhe denounc'd my death, ſhe ſeem'd to promiſe grace.</l>
               <l>So ſhall I feeme in ſhow my thoughts for to repoſe,</l>
               <l>Yet in the center of my ſoule ſhall ſhroud a world of woes:</l>
               <l>Then wofull breſt and eyes your reſtleſſe courſe controule,</l>
               <l>And with no outward ſignes betray the anguiſh of my ſoule.</l>
               <l>Eyes raine your ſhoures within, arrowze the Earth no more,</l>
               <l>Paſſe drowne with a deluge of teares the breſt ye burnt before:</l>
               <l>Breſt arme your ſelfe with ſighes, if ore weake to defend,</l>
               <l>Then periſh by your proper fires, and make an honeſt end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Song</hi> 4.</head>
               <l>O Bitter time that doſt begin the yeare,</l>
               <l>And doſt begin each bitter thing to breed!</l>
               <l>O ſeaſon ſowre, that ſeaſon'ſt ſo with gall</l>
               <l>Each kind of <hi>thing,</hi> in thee that life doth take;</l>
               <l>Yet cloak'ſt thy ſowreneſſe with a ſweet-like hew,</l>
               <l>And for my <hi>ſhare</hi> doſt make me ſtill to pine,</l>
               <l>As one that's rob'd of reſt.</l>
               <l>Now when through all the earth the baſeſt brire,</l>
               <l>In ſigne of ioy is cloath'd with Sommers weed,</l>
               <l>Euen now when as hils, herbes, woods, vales and all,</l>
               <l>Begin to <hi>ſpring,</hi> and off th'old ruines ſhake,</l>
               <l>Thou but begin'ſt mine anguiſh to renew;</l>
               <l>O rigour <hi>rare,</hi> to baniſh me from mine,</l>
               <l>When birds do build their neſt.</l>
               <l>By theſe thy fierce effects it may appeare,</l>
               <l>That with the Bull the Sunne ſoiournes indeed.</l>
               <l>What ſauage Bull disbanded from his ſtall,</l>
               <l>Of wrath a <hi>signe</hi> more inhumane could make?</l>
               <l>Ore all the Earth thou powr'ſt downe pleaſant dew:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:19"/>
               <l>But with <hi>deſpaire</hi> doſt all my hopes confine,</l>
               <l>With teares to bath my breſt.</l>
               <l>Now when the time t'increaſe is drawing neare,</l>
               <l>Thou in my breſt of ſorrow ſow'ſt the ſeed,</l>
               <l>And thoſe old griefes thou goeſt for to recall,</l>
               <l>That fading <hi>hing</hi> and would the ſtalke forſake.</l>
               <l>Thus how can I ſome huge miſhap eſchew,</l>
               <l>Who kil'd with <hi>care,</hi> all comfort muſt reſigne,</l>
               <l>And yeeld to th'amorous peſt?</l>
               <l>The heau'n of my eſtate growes neuer cleare,</l>
               <l>I many torments feele, yet worſe do dread:</l>
               <l>Miſhaps haue me inuiron'd with a wall,</l>
               <l>And my heart <hi>ſting</hi> with paines that neuer ſlake:</l>
               <l>Yet to the end Ile to my Deare be true;</l>
               <l>So this ſharpe <hi>aire</hi> my conſtancie ſhall fine,</l>
               <l>Which may come for the beſt.</l>
               <l>Ile write my woes vpon this Pine-tree here,</l>
               <l>That paſſengers ſuch rarities may reade,</l>
               <l>Who when they thinke of this my wretched fall,</l>
               <l>With ſighes may <hi>ſing</hi> thoſe euils that make me quake,</l>
               <l>And for compaſſion waile, while as they view,</l>
               <l>How that I <hi>there</hi> with ſuch a ſauage line,</l>
               <l>A tyrants Trophees dreſt.</l>
               <l>This time deſir'd of all Ile to hold deare,</l>
               <l>And as that all things now to flouriſh ſpeed:</l>
               <l>So mouing on this ſea-inuiron'd ball,</l>
               <l>Foorth teares to <hi>bring</hi> mine eyes ſhall euer wake:</l>
               <l>And whilſt euen ſenſleſſe things my ſorrowes rue,</l>
               <l>I ſhall not <hi>ſpare</hi> no part of my ingine,</l>
               <l>My ſelfe for to moleſt.</l>
               <l>The ſoureſt hearbes ſhall be my ſweeteſt cheare,</l>
               <l>Since to prolong my paines I onely feed;</l>
               <l>Some dungeon darke ſhall ſerue me for a hall,</l>
               <l>And like a <hi>king</hi> I ſhall companions lake.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:20"/>
               <l>Though neuer Enuie do my ſtate purſue,</l>
               <l>Of wormwood <hi>bare</hi> I mind to make my wine,</l>
               <l>Thus ſhall I be diſtreſt.</l>
               <l>For ſince my <hi>Faire</hi> doth not vpon me rue,</l>
               <l>My hopes ſet in the weſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 31.</head>
               <l>MY faireſt Faire aduiſe thee with thy heart,</l>
               <l>And tell in time if that thou think'ſt to loue me,</l>
               <l>Leſt that I periſh whil'ſt thou think'ſt to proue me,</l>
               <l>And ſo thou want the meanes to act thy part:</l>
               <l>For I account my ſelfe ſo done accurſt,</l>
               <l>That from deſpaires refuge I ſcarce refraine.</l>
               <l>The daintieſt colours do the ſooneſt ſtaine,</l>
               <l>And the moſt noble minds do ſooneſt burſt.</l>
               <l>Why ſhouldſt thou thus thy rareſt treaſure venter?</l>
               <l>Lo, all the waightie thoughts, the burd'nous cares,</l>
               <l>And euery horror that the health impaires,</l>
               <l>Draw to the heart, as to the bodies Center:</l>
               <l>And it ore-ballanc'd with ſo great a waight,</l>
               <l>Doth boaſt to yeeld vnto the burthen ſtraight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 32.</head>
               <l>THe turret of my hope which neuer falles,</l>
               <l>Did at the firſt all <hi>Cupids</hi> power deſpiſe:</l>
               <l>But it t'orethrow while as thou arm'd thine eyes;</l>
               <l>Thy lookes were Canons, thy diſdaines their balles:</l>
               <l>I brau'd thy beauties in a gallant ſort,</l>
               <l>And did reſiſt all thy aſſaults a time:</l>
               <l>But ah, I find in end, (my wrack thy crime)</l>
               <l>That treaſon enters in the ſtrongeſt fort.</l>
               <l>Thou ſeeing thou waſt like to loſe the field,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:20"/>
               <l>Vnto my thoughts ſome fauour didſt impart,</l>
               <l>Which like brib'd Orators inform'd the hart,</l>
               <l>The victor would proue kind, if I could yeeld:</l>
               <l>And ô, what can this grace thy beauties ſtraines?</l>
               <l>T'is no true victorie that treaſon gaines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 33.</head>
               <l>O If thou knew'ſt how thou thy ſelfe doſt harme,</l>
               <l>And doſt preiudge thy bliſſe, and ſpoile my reſt:</l>
               <l>Then thou would'ſt melt the yce out of thy breſt,</l>
               <l>And thy relenting heart would kindly warme.</l>
               <l>O if thy pride did not our ioyes controule,</l>
               <l>What world of louing wonders ſhould'ſt thou ſee!</l>
               <l>For if I ſaw thee once transform'd in me,</l>
               <l>Then in thy boſome I would poure my ſoule,</l>
               <l>Then all thy thoughts ſhould in my viſage ſhine.</l>
               <l>And if that ought miſchanc'd thou ſhould'ſt not mone,</l>
               <l>Nor beare the burthen of thy griefes alone;</l>
               <l>No, I would haue my ſhare in what were thine.</l>
               <l>And whil'ſt we thus ſhould make our ſorrowes one,</l>
               <l>This happie harmonie would make them none.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 34.</head>
               <l>WHat vncouth motion makes my mirth decay?</l>
               <l>Is this the thing poore martyr'd men call Loue?</l>
               <l>And whil'ſt their torment doth their wits diſmay,</l>
               <l>As thoſe that raue, do for a god approue?</l>
               <l>Although he bring his greatneſſe from aboue,</l>
               <l>And rule the world according to his will,</l>
               <l>Yet doth he euen from thoſe all reſt remoue,</l>
               <l>That were deuoted to his deitie ſtill.</l>
               <l>Can that which is th'originall of ill,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:21"/>
               <l>From which doth flow an Ocean of miſchiefe,</l>
               <l>Whoſe poyſnous waues doth many thouſands kill</l>
               <l>Can that be loue? no, t'is the ſource of griefe.</l>
               <l>And all thoſe erre that hold this vaine conceit;</l>
               <l>Then I erre too, one in this ſame eſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Seſtin.</hi> 2.</head>
               <l>WHile as the day deliuers vs his light,</l>
               <l>I wander through the ſolitarie fields,</l>
               <l>And when the euening hath obſcur'd the earth,</l>
               <l>And hath with ſilence lull'd the world aſleepe:</l>
               <l>Then rage I like a mad-man in my bed,</l>
               <l>Which being fir'd with ſighes, I quench with teares.</l>
               <l>But ere <hi>Aurora</hi> riſe to ſpend her teares,</l>
               <l>Still languiſhing againe to ſee the light,</l>
               <l>As th'enemie of my reſt, I flie my bed,</l>
               <l>And take me to the moſt deſerted fields:</l>
               <l>There is no ſoule ſaue I but gets ſome ſleepe,</l>
               <l>Though one would ſeeke through all the peopled earth.</l>
               <l>Whiles th'<hi>Aetna</hi> of my fires affrights the earth,</l>
               <l>And whiles it dreads, I drowne it with my teares:</l>
               <l>And it's ſuſpicious-like, I neither ſleepe,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Phoebus</hi> giues nor gathers in his light:</l>
               <l>So many piles of graſſe not cloath the fields,</l>
               <l>As I deuiſe deſignes within my bed.</l>
               <l>Vnto the time I find a froſtie bed,</l>
               <l>Digged within the bowels of the earth,</l>
               <l>Mine eyes ſalt flouds ſhall ſtill oreflow the fields:</l>
               <l>I looke not for an abſtinence from teares,</l>
               <l>Till firſt I be ſecluded from the light,</l>
               <l>And end my torments with an endleſſe ſleepe.</l>
               <l>For now when I am purpoſed to ſleepe,</l>
               <l>A thouſand thoughts aſſaile me in my bed,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:21"/>
               <l>That oft I do deſpaire to ſee the light:</l>
               <l>O would to God I were diſſolu'd in earth;</l>
               <l>Then would the ſauage beaſts bemone with teares,</l>
               <l>Their neighbours death through all th'vnpeopled fields.</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt rauiſh'd whiles I walke alongſt the fields,</l>
               <l>The lookers on lament, I loſe my ſleepe:</l>
               <l>But of the <hi>Crocadiles</hi> thoſe be the teares,</l>
               <l>So to perſwade me for to go to ſleepe;</l>
               <l>As being ſure, when once I leaue the light,</l>
               <l>To render me the greateſt wretch on th'earth.</l>
               <l>O happieſt I in th'earth, if in the fields,</l>
               <l>I might ſtill ſee the light and neuer ſleepe,</l>
               <l>Drinking ſalt teares, and making ſtones my bed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 35.</head>
               <l>WHen I behold that face for which I pin'd,</l>
               <l>And did my ſelfe ſo long in vaine annoy,</l>
               <l>My toung not able to vnfold my ioy,</l>
               <l>A wondring ſilence onely ſhewes my mind:</l>
               <l>But when againe thou doſt extend thy rigour,</l>
               <l>And wilt not daigne to grace me with thy ſight,</l>
               <l>Thou kil'ſt my comfort, and ſo ſpoil'ſt my might,</l>
               <l>That ſcarce my corps retaines the vitall vigour.</l>
               <l>Thy preſence thus a great contentment brings,</l>
               <l>And is my ſoules ineſtimable treaſure:</l>
               <l>But ô, I drowne in th'Ocean of diſpleaſure,</l>
               <l>When I in abſence thinke vpon thoſe things.</l>
               <l>Thus would to God that I had ſeene thee neuer,</l>
               <l>Or would to God that I might ſee thee euer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sonet</hi> 36.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>LOyr,</hi> witneſſe thou what was my ſpotleſſe part,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt thou amaz'd to ſee thy Nymphes ſo faire,</l>
               <l>As loth to part thence where they did repaire,</l>
               <l>Still murm'ring did thy plaints t'each ſtone impart:</l>
               <l>Then did mine eyes betake them to my hart,</l>
               <l>As ſcorning to behold all thoſe, though rare,</l>
               <l>And gaz'd vpon her beauties image there,</l>
               <l>Whoſe eyes haue furniſh'd <hi>Cupid</hi> many a dart:</l>
               <l>And as deuoted only vnto her,</l>
               <l>They did diſdaine for to beſtow their light,</l>
               <l>For to be entertain'd with any ſight,</l>
               <l>Saue onely that which made them firſt to erre.</l>
               <l>Then famous riuer through the Ocean glide,</l>
               <l>And tell my loue how conſtant I abide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 37.</head>
               <l>I Cannot comprehend how this doth come,</l>
               <l>Thou whoſe affections neuer yet were warme,</l>
               <l>Which cold diſdaine with leaden thoughts doth arme:</l>
               <l>Though in thy ſelfe ſtill cold, yet burn'ſt thou ſome.</l>
               <l>Euen as the Sunne (as th'Aſtrologian dreames)</l>
               <l>In th'airie region where it ſelfe doth moue,</l>
               <l>Is neuer hote, yet darting from aboue,</l>
               <l>Doth parch all things that repercuſſe his beames:</l>
               <l>So thou that in thy ſelfe from fires art free,</l>
               <l>Who eye's indifferent ſtill, as <hi>Titans</hi> ſtayes,</l>
               <l>Whilſt I am th'obiect that reflect thy rayes:</l>
               <l>That which thou neuer hadſt, thou workſt in me.</l>
               <l>Since but below thou ſhew'ſt that power of thine,</l>
               <l>I would the <hi>Zodiacke</hi> be whence thou doſt ſhine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 38.</head>
               <l>MY teares might all the parched ſands haue drench'd,</l>
               <l>Though <hi>Phaeton</hi> had vndone the liquide frame:</l>
               <l>Ile furniſh <hi>Vulcans</hi> fornace with a flame,</l>
               <l>That like the <hi>Vestals</hi> fire was neuer quench'd.</l>
               <l>And though th'infected aire turmoil'd remaine,</l>
               <l>It by my ſighes and cries may be refin'd:</l>
               <l>And if the bodie anſwer to the mind,</l>
               <l>If no earth were, mine might make th'earth againe:</l>
               <l>Though all the ſauage flockes lay dead in heapes,</l>
               <l>With which th' <hi>Arabian</hi> deſarts are beſt ſtor'd,</l>
               <l>My breſt might many a fiercer beaſt affoord,</l>
               <l>If like themſelues all cloath'd with monſtrous ſhapes:</l>
               <l>And thus within my ſelfe I create ſo,</l>
               <l>A world with all the Elements of wo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 39.</head>
               <l>MVſt I attend an vnrelenting will,</l>
               <l>Which neuer any ſigne of fauour ſhew?</l>
               <l>Ah, why ſhould'ſt thou <hi>Aurora</hi> thus purſue</l>
               <l>An innocent, that neuer did thee ill?</l>
               <l>I did not with the Greeke conſpire to kill</l>
               <l>Thy ſonne, for whom thou ſhed'ſt ſuch flouds of dew:</l>
               <l>But I as one that yet his deſtine rue,</l>
               <l>For to condole with thee, huge teares diſtill;</l>
               <l>And like the louing birds that came each yeare,</l>
               <l>Vpon his tombe to offer vp their bloud:</l>
               <l>So ſhall I too powre foorth a skarlet floud,</l>
               <l>And ſacrifize a heart that holds thee deare:</l>
               <l>That ſince my life to make thee loue lackes force,</l>
               <l>At leaſt my death may moue thee to remorce.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 40.</head>
               <l>THy cruelties (fierce Faire) may be excus'd:</l>
               <l>For it was I that gaue thy beautie powre,</l>
               <l>And taught thee when to ſmile, and when to lowre,</l>
               <l>Which thou haſt ſince ſtill to my ruine vs'd:</l>
               <l>As he that others purpos'd was to pine,</l>
               <l>And for his braſen bull a guerdon claim'd,</l>
               <l>Was tortur'd firſt with that which he had fram'd,</l>
               <l>And made th'experience of his curſt engine:</l>
               <l>So in this manner doſt thou me torment,</l>
               <l>Who told thee firſt the force of thy diſdaines:</l>
               <l>But ah, I ſuffer many greater paines,</l>
               <l>Then the <hi>Sicilian</hi> tyrants could inuent:</l>
               <l>And yet this grieues me moſt that thou diſgrac'd,</l>
               <l>Art in the rancke with ſuch like tyrants plac'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 41.</head>
               <l>IF that ſo many braue men leauing <hi>Greece,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Durſt earſt aduenter through the raging depth,</l>
               <l>And all to get the ſpoiles of a poore ſheepe,</l>
               <l>That had bene famous for his golden fleece.</l>
               <l>O then for that pure gold what ſhould be ſought,</l>
               <l>Of which each haire is worth a thouſand ſuch!</l>
               <l>No doubt for it one cannot do too much.</l>
               <l>Why ſhould not precious things be dearely bought?</l>
               <l>And ſo they are, for in the <hi>Colchik</hi> guiſe,</l>
               <l>This treaſure many a danger doth defend:</l>
               <l>Of which, when I haue brought ſome one to end,</l>
               <l>Straight out of that a number doth ariſe:</l>
               <l>Euen as the Dragons teeth bred men at armes,</l>
               <l>Which (ah) t'orethrow, I want <hi>Medeas</hi> charmes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 42.</head>
               <l>OFt with that mirror would I change my ſhape,</l>
               <l>From which my Faire askes counſell euery day,</l>
               <l>How ſhe th'vntainted beauties ſhould array,</l>
               <l>To th'end their fierce aſſaults no ſoule may ſcape.</l>
               <l>Then in my boſome I behoou'd t'imbrace</l>
               <l>That which I loue, and whilſt on me ſhe gaz'd,</l>
               <l>In her ſweet eyes I many a time amaz'd,</l>
               <l>Would woo my ſelfe, and borrow thence a grace.</l>
               <l>But ah, I ſeeke that which I haue, and more,</l>
               <l>She but too oft in me her picture ſpies,</l>
               <l>And I but gaze too oft on thoſe faire eyes,</l>
               <l>Whence I the humor draw that makes mine ſore.</l>
               <l>Well may my loue come glaſſe her ſelfe in me,</l>
               <l>In whom all what ſhe is, the world may ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 43.</head>
               <l>NOw when the <hi>Syren</hi> ſings, as one diſmaid,</l>
               <l>I ſtraight with waxe begin to ſtop mine eares;</l>
               <l>And when the <hi>Crocadile</hi> doth ſhed foorth teares,</l>
               <l>I flie away, for feare to be betraid.</l>
               <l>I know when as thou ſeem'ſt to waile my ſtate,</l>
               <l>Thy face is no true table of thy mind:</l>
               <l>And thou wouldſt neuer ſhew thy ſelfe ſo kind,</l>
               <l>Wert not thy thoughts are hatching ſome deceit:</l>
               <l>Whilſt with vaine hopes thou go'ſt about to fill me.</l>
               <l>I wot whereto thoſe drams of fauour tend;</l>
               <l>Leſt by my death thy cruelties ſhould end,</l>
               <l>Thou think'ſt by giuing life againe to kill me:</l>
               <l>No, no, thou ſhalt not thus thy greatneſſe raiſe,</l>
               <l>Ile breake the trumpet that proclaim'd thy praiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 44.</head>
               <l>O Now I thinke, and do not thinke amiſſe,</l>
               <l>That th'old Philoſophers were all but fooles,</l>
               <l>Who vs'd ſuch curious queſtions in their ſchooles,</l>
               <l>Yet could not apprehend the higheſt Bliſſe.</l>
               <l>Lo, I haue learn'd in th'Academe of Loue,</l>
               <l>A Maxime which they neuer vnderſtood:</l>
               <l>To loue and be belou'd this is the good,</l>
               <l>Which for moſt ſou'raigne all the world will proue,</l>
               <l>That which delights vs moſt muſt be our treaſure:</l>
               <l>And to what greater ioy can one aſpire,</l>
               <l>Then to poſſeſſe all that he doth deſire,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt two vnited ſoules do melt in pleaſure?</l>
               <l>This is the greateſt good can be inuented,</l>
               <l>That is ſo great it cannot be augmented.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 45.</head>
               <l>I Wonder not at <hi>Procris</hi> raging fits,</l>
               <l>Who was afraid of thy entangling grace:</l>
               <l>O there be many ſorcerers in thy face,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Magicke may enchaunt the rareſt wits.</l>
               <l>To <hi>Cephalus</hi> what would thy lookes haue bred,</l>
               <l>When thou while as the world thy ſight purſude,</l>
               <l>As bluſhing of ſo many to be viewd,</l>
               <l>A vale of roſes ore thy beauties ſpred:</l>
               <l>Then euer gazing on thine yuorie browes,</l>
               <l>He wounded with thy Chriſtall-pointed eyes,</l>
               <l>Had rear'd a Trophee to the morning skies,</l>
               <l>Not mindfull of his <hi>Hymenean</hi> vowes.</l>
               <l>But I am glad it chanc'd not to be ſo,</l>
               <l>Leaſt I had partner bene of <hi>Procris</hi> wo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 46.</head>
               <l>LOue ſwore hy <hi>Styx</hi> whilſt all the depths did tremble,</l>
               <l>That he would be aueng'd of my proud hart,</l>
               <l>Who to his Deitie durſt baſe ſtyles impart,</l>
               <l>And would in that <hi>Latona's</hi> impe reſemble:</l>
               <l>Then ſtraight denounc'd his rebell, in a rage</l>
               <l>He labour'd by all meanes for to betray me,</l>
               <l>And gaue full leaue to any for to ſlay me,</l>
               <l>That he might by my wracke his wrath aſſwage:</l>
               <l>A Nymph that long'd to finiſh <hi>Cupids</hi> toyles,</l>
               <l>Chanc'd once to ſpie me come in beauties bounds,</l>
               <l>And ſtraight orethrew me with world of wounds,</l>
               <l>Then vnto <hi>Paphos</hi> did tranſport my ſpoiles.</l>
               <l>Thus, thus I ſee, that all muſt fall in end,</l>
               <l>That with a greater then themſelues contend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Song</hi> 7.</head>
               <l>A Longſt the borders of a pleaſant plaine,</l>
               <l>The ſad <hi>Alexis</hi> did his garments teare,</l>
               <l>And though alone, yet fearing to be plaine,</l>
               <l>Did maime his words with many a ſigh and teare:</l>
               <l>For whilſt he lean'd him downe vpon a greene,</l>
               <l>His wounds againe began for to grow greene.</l>
               <l>At laſt in ſhow as one whoſe hopes were light,</l>
               <l>From fainting breath he forc'd thoſe words to part:</l>
               <l>O deare <hi>Aurora,</hi> dearer then the light,</l>
               <l>Of all the worlds delights mine onely part:</l>
               <l>How long ſhall I in barren fields thus eare,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt to my ſad laments thou lend'ſt no eare!</l>
               <l>O what a rage doth boyle in euery vaine,</l>
               <l>Which ſhewes the world my better part's not ſound:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:25"/>
               <l>And yet thou let'ſt me ſpend thoſe plaints in vaine,</l>
               <l>T'amaze the world with many a mournfull ſound:</l>
               <l>And whilſt that I to griefe enlarge the raines,</l>
               <l>A ſhoure of ſorrow ore my viſage raines.</l>
               <l>Ah, what haue I whereon my hopes to found,</l>
               <l>That hop'd t'haue had repoſe within thine arme,</l>
               <l>Yet haue not any ſigne of fauour found,</l>
               <l>Thy marble mind ſuch frozen fancies arme:</l>
               <l>For when in humble ſort for grace I pray,</l>
               <l>Thou triumph'ſt ore me, as thy beauties pray.</l>
               <l>I that tranſported once was neare gone wood,</l>
               <l>Now with long trauels growing faint and leane,</l>
               <l>While as I wander through the defart wood,</l>
               <l>My wearied bodie on each tree muſt leane:</l>
               <l>And whil'ſt my heart is with ſtrange <hi>Harpies</hi> rent,</l>
               <l>I pay to ſorrow the accuſtom'd rent.</l>
               <l>And whil'ſt I wander like the wounded Deere,</l>
               <l>That ſeekes for <hi>Dictamne</hi> to recure his ſcarre,</l>
               <l>And come to thee whom I hold onely deere,</l>
               <l>Thou doſt (fierce Faire) at my diſaſter ſcarre:</l>
               <l>And mak'ſt me from all kind of comfort barr'd,</l>
               <l>Liue in the deſerts like a raging <hi>Bard.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ah, be there now no meanes t'vndo the band,</l>
               <l>That thou haſt fram'd of thoſe thy golden lockes!</l>
               <l>Ile range my fancies in a deſperate band,</l>
               <l>And burſt aſunder all thy beauties lockes:</l>
               <l>Then to thy breſt thoſe firie troupes will lead,</l>
               <l>There from about thy heart to melt the lead.</l>
               <l>But ah, I boaſt in vaine, this cannot be,</l>
               <l>Although my ſelfe to many ſhapes I turne:</l>
               <l>I onely labour like the reſtleſſe Bee,</l>
               <l>That toyles in vaine to ſerue anothers turne.</l>
               <l>My hopes which once wing'd with thy fauours roſe,</l>
               <l>Are falling now, as doth the blaſted roſe.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:25"/>
               <l>That thoſe my torments cannot long time laſt,</l>
               <l>In my declining eyes the world may reade,</l>
               <l>Lo wounded with thy pride I fall at laſt,</l>
               <l>As doth before the winds a beaten reed:</l>
               <l>And this my death with ſhame thy cheekes may die,</l>
               <l>Since ſacrific'd to thy diſdaine I die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 47.</head>
               <l>WHen whiles I heare ſome gallants to giue forth,</l>
               <l>That thoſe whom they adore are onely faire,</l>
               <l>With whom they thinke none other can compare;</l>
               <l>The beautie of beautie, and the height of worth,</l>
               <l>Then Iealouſie doth all my ioyes controule,</l>
               <l>For ô I thinke, who can accompliſh'd be,</l>
               <l>(There is no Sunne but one) ſaue onely ſhe</l>
               <l>Whom I haue made the idole of my ſoule;</l>
               <l>And this ſuſpition wounds my better parts:</l>
               <l>I rage to haue a riuall in my light,</l>
               <l>And yet would rage farre more, if any might</l>
               <l>Giue her their eyes, and yet hold backe their hearts;</l>
               <l>Too great affection doth thoſe paſſions moue,</l>
               <l>I may not truſt my ſhadow with my loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 48.</head>
               <l>WHen as I come to thy reſpected ſight,</l>
               <l>Thy lookes are all ſo chaſt, thy words ſo graue,</l>
               <l>That my affections do the foile receaue,</l>
               <l>And like to darknes yeeld vnto the light;</l>
               <l>Still vertue holds the ballance of thy wit,</l>
               <l>In which great reaſon ponders euery thought,</l>
               <l>And thou deare Ladie neuer ſtaind in ought,</l>
               <l>Thus ore thy ſelfe doſt as an Empreſſe ſit.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:26"/>
               <l>O what is beautie if not free from blame,</l>
               <l>It haue the ſoule as white as is the skinne,</l>
               <l>The froth of vanitie, the dregs of ſinne,</l>
               <l>A wracke to others, to it ſelfe a ſhame;</l>
               <l>And as it is moſt precious if kept pure,</l>
               <l>It is as much abhorr'd if once impure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Song</hi> 6.</head>
               <l>WHen ſilence luls the world aſleepe,</l>
               <l>And ſtarres do glance in th'Azure field,</l>
               <l>The mountaines making ſhadowes ore the plaines,</l>
               <l>All creatures then betake themſelues to reſt,</l>
               <l>And to the law of nature yeeld,</l>
               <l>Saue I, who no good order keepe,</l>
               <l>That then begin to feele my paines;</l>
               <l>For in the Zodiacke of my breſt,</l>
               <l>The Sunne that I adore her light reuiues,</l>
               <l>Whilſt wearied <hi>Phoebus</hi> in the Ocean diues.</l>
               <l>The worlds cleare day was night to me,</l>
               <l>Who ſeem'd aſleepe ſtill in a trance,</l>
               <l>And all my words were ſpoken through a dreame:</l>
               <l>But then when th'earth puts on th'vmbragious maske,</l>
               <l>My paſſions do themſelues aduance,</l>
               <l>And from thoſe outward lets ſet free,</l>
               <l>That had them earſt reſtrain'd with ſhame,</l>
               <l>Do ſet me to my wofull taske:</l>
               <l>Then from the night her priuiledge I take,</l>
               <l>And in diſpight of <hi>Morpheus</hi> I will wake.</l>
               <l>But ſtraight the Sunne that giues melight,</l>
               <l>With many duskiſh vapors cled,</l>
               <l>Doth ſeeme to boaſt me with ſome feareful ſtorme;</l>
               <l>And whilſt I gaze vpon the glorious beames,</l>
               <l>Lo metamorphos'd in my bed,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:26"/>
               <l>I loſe at once my ſhapher ſight;</l>
               <l>And taking on another forme,</l>
               <l>Am all diſſolu'd in bitter ſtreames,</l>
               <l>Where many monſters bathe themſelues anone,</l>
               <l>At which ſtrange ſight the Faunes and Satyres mone.</l>
               <l>But whilſt I ſeeke mo ſprings t'aſſemble,</l>
               <l>My waters are dride vp againe,</l>
               <l>And as the mightie Giant that <hi>Ioue</hi> tames:</l>
               <l>I wot not whether, if thundred or thundring,</l>
               <l>Againſt the heau'ns ſmokes forth diſdaine,</l>
               <l>And makes mount <hi>Aetna</hi> tremble.</l>
               <l>So I ſend forth a flood of flames,</l>
               <l>Which makes the world for to ſtand wondring,</l>
               <l>And neuer did the Lemnian furnace burne,</l>
               <l>As then my breſt, whilſt all to fire I turne.</l>
               <l>At laſt no conſtancie below,</l>
               <l>Thus plagued in two diuers ſhapes,</l>
               <l>I'm turn'd into my ſelfe, and then I quake,</l>
               <l>For this I haue by proofe found worſt of all:</l>
               <l>Then do my hopes fall dead in heapes,</l>
               <l>And to b'aueng'd of their ouerthrow,</l>
               <l>Strange troupes of thoughts their muſters make,</l>
               <l>Which toſſe my fancie like a ball:</l>
               <l>Thus one miſhap doth come as th'other's paſt,</l>
               <l>And ſtill the greateſt croſſe comes euer laſt.</l>
               <l>To tell the ſtarres my night I paſſe,</l>
               <l>And much conclude, yet queſtions do ariſe;</l>
               <l>I harrengues make though dumbe, and ſee though blind,</l>
               <l>And though alone, am hem'd about with bands:</l>
               <l>I build great caſtels in the skies,</l>
               <l>Whoſe tender turrets but of glaſſe,</l>
               <l>Are ſtraight oreturn'd with euery wind,</l>
               <l>And rear'd and raz'd, yet without hands;</l>
               <l>I in this ſtate ſtrange miſeries detect,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:27"/>
               <l>And more deuiſe then thouſands can effect.</l>
               <l>My Sunne whilſt thus I ſtand perplex'd,</l>
               <l>The darknſſe doth Igaine controule,</l>
               <l>And then I gaze vpon that diuine grace,</l>
               <l>Which as that I had view'd <hi>Meduſaes</hi> head,</l>
               <l>Transform'd me once; and my ſad ſoule,</l>
               <l>That thus hath bene ſo ſtrangely vext,</l>
               <l>Doth from her ſeate thoſe troubles chaſe,</l>
               <l>The which before diſpaire had made,</l>
               <l>And all her pow'r vpon contentment feeds,</l>
               <l>No ioy to that which after wo ſucceeds.</l>
               <l>And yet thoſe dainties of my ioyes,</l>
               <l>Are ſtill confected with ſome feares,</l>
               <l>That well accuſtom'd with my cruell fate,</l>
               <l>Can neuer truſt the gift that th'enemie giues,</l>
               <l>And onely th'end true witneſſe beares:</l>
               <l>For whilſt my ſoule her pow'r imployes,</l>
               <l>To ſurfet in this happie ſtate,</l>
               <l>The heau'n againe my wracke contriues,</l>
               <l>And the worlds Sunne enuying this of mine,</l>
               <l>To darken my loues world begins to ſhine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 49.</head>
               <l>I Thinke that <hi>Cipris</hi> in a high diſdaine,</l>
               <l>Barr'd by the barb'rous Turkes that conquer'd ſeate,</l>
               <l>To re-erect the ruines of her ſtate,</l>
               <l>Comes ore their bounds t'eſtabliſh beauties raigne;</l>
               <l>And whilſt her greatneſſe doth begin to riſe,</l>
               <l>As ſdaining temples built of baſer frame,</l>
               <l>She in thoſe roſie ſnowes t'enſtall her name,</l>
               <l>Reares ſtately altars in thy ſtarrie eyes,</l>
               <l>Before whoſe ſacred ſhrine deuinely faire,</l>
               <l>Breſts boyling ſtill with generous deſires,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:27"/>
               <l>Fall ſacrific'd with memorable fires;</l>
               <l>The incenſe of whoſe ſighes endeers the aire,</l>
               <l>In which thy ſame vnparagond doth flee,</l>
               <l>Whilſt thou by beautie, beautie liues by thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 50.</head>
               <l>ONce <hi>Cupid</hi> had compaſſion of my ſtate,</l>
               <l>And wounded with a wonderfull remorce,</l>
               <l>Vow'd that he would my cruell faire enforce,</l>
               <l>To melt the rigor of her cold conceit:</l>
               <l>But when he came his purpoſe to fulfill,</l>
               <l>And ſhot at her a volly from the skies,</l>
               <l>She did receiue the darts within her eyes;</l>
               <l>Then in thoſe criſtall quiuers kept them ſtill.</l>
               <l>Who vaunt before they win, oft loſe the game;</l>
               <l>And the preſumptuous mind gets manieſt foiles.</l>
               <l>Lo he that thought t'haue triumph'd ore her ſpoiles,</l>
               <l>But come with pride, and went away with ſhame:</l>
               <l>And where he hop'd t'haue helpd me by this ſtrife,</l>
               <l>He brought her armes wherewith to take my life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 51.</head>
               <l>I Dream'd the Nymph that ore my fancie raignes,</l>
               <l>Came to a part whereas I paus'd alone;</l>
               <l>Then ſaid, what needs you in ſuch ſort to mone?</l>
               <l>Haue I not power to recompence your paines?</l>
               <l>Lo I coniure you by that loyall loue,</l>
               <l>Which you profeſſe, to caſt thoſe griefes apart,</l>
               <l>It's long deare loue ſince that you had my hart,</l>
               <l>Yet I was coy your conſtancie to proue,</l>
               <l>But hauing had a proofe, Ile now be free:</l>
               <l>I am the Eccho that your ſighes reſounds,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:28"/>
               <l>Your woes are mine, I ſuffer in your wounds,</l>
               <l>Your paſſions all they ſympathize in me:</l>
               <l>Thus whilſt for kindneſſe both began to weepe,</l>
               <l>My happineſſe euaniſh'd with the ſleepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 52.</head>
               <l>SOme men delight huge buildings to behold,</l>
               <l>Some theaters, mountaines, floods, and famous ſprings;</l>
               <l>Some monuments of Monarkes, and ſuch things</l>
               <l>As in the bookes of fame haue bene inrol'd:</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſtately townes that to the ſtarres were rais'd,</l>
               <l>Some would their ruines ſee (their beautie's gone)</l>
               <l>Of which the worlds three parts, each boſts of one,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Caeſar, Hanniball,</hi> and <hi>Hector</hi> prais'd:</l>
               <l>Though none of thoſe, I loue a ſight as rare,</l>
               <l>Euen her that ore my life as Queene doth ſit,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iuno</hi> in maieſtie, <hi>Pallas</hi> in wit;</l>
               <l>As <hi>Phoebe</hi> chaſt, then <hi>Venus</hi> farre more faire:</l>
               <l>And though her lookes euen threaten death to me.</l>
               <l>Their threatnings are ſo ſweet I cannot flie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 53.</head>
               <l>IF now cleare Po, that pittie be not ſpent,</l>
               <l>Which for to quench his flames did once thee moue,</l>
               <l>Whom the great thunderer thundred from aboue,</l>
               <l>And to thy ſiluer boſome burning ſent,</l>
               <l>To pitie his coequall be content;</l>
               <l>That in effect doth the like fortune proue,</l>
               <l>Throwne headlong from the higheſt heau'ns of loue:</l>
               <l>Here burning on thy borders I lament,</l>
               <l>The ſucceſſe did not ſecond my diſſigne,</l>
               <l>Yet muſt I like my generous intent,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:28"/>
               <l>Which cannot be condemn'd by the euent,</l>
               <l>That fault was fortunes, though the loſſe be mine;</l>
               <l>And by my fall I ſhall be honor'd oft,</l>
               <l>My fall doth witneſſe I was once aloft.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 54.</head>
               <l>GReat God that guides the Dolphin through the deepe,</l>
               <l>Looke now as thou didſt then with ſmiling grace,</l>
               <l>When ſeeking once her beauties to embrace,</l>
               <l>Thou forc'd the faire <hi>Amimone</hi> to weepe:</l>
               <l>The liquid monarchie thou canſt not keepe,</l>
               <l>If thus the bluſtring God vſurp thy place;</l>
               <l>Riſe and againſt his blaſts erect thy face;</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Tritons</hi> trumpet ſound the ſeas aſleepe,</l>
               <l>With thine owne armes the wind thy boſome wounds,</l>
               <l>And whilſt that it thy followers fall contriues,</l>
               <l>Thy Trident to indanger dayly ſtriues,</l>
               <l>And deſolate would render all thy bounds:</l>
               <l>Then if thou think'ſt for to preſerue thy ſtate,</l>
               <l>Let not ſuch ſtormes diſturb thy watrie ſeate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 55.</head>
               <l>I Enuie <hi>Neptune</hi> oft, not that his hands</l>
               <l>Did build that loftie Ilions ſtately towers,</l>
               <l>Nor that he Emperour of the liquid pow'rs,</l>
               <l>Doth brooke a place amongſt the'immortall bands,</l>
               <l>But that embracing her whom I loue beſt,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Achilous</hi> with <hi>Alcides</hi> once,</l>
               <l>Still wreſtling with the riuall earth he grones,</l>
               <l>For earneſtnes t'ouerflow her happieneſt:</l>
               <l>Thus would he barre me from her preſence ſtill,</l>
               <l>For when I come a field, he faun'd my ſailes,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:29"/>
               <l>With mild <hi>Zephires</hi> faire yet proſprous gailes,</l>
               <l>And like t'<hi>Vlyſſes</hi> gaue me wind at will:</l>
               <l>But when I would returne, O what deceit</l>
               <l>With tumbling waues thou barr'ſt the glaſſie gate!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 56.</head>
               <l>LO, now reuiuing my diſaſt'rous ſtile,</l>
               <l>I proſecute the tenor of my fate,</l>
               <l>And follow forth at dangers higheſt rate,</l>
               <l>In forraine Realmes my fortune for a while:</l>
               <l>I might haue learn'd this by my laſt exile,</l>
               <l>That change of countries cannot change my ſtate:</l>
               <l>Where euer that my bodie ſeeke a ſeate,</l>
               <l>I leaue my heart in Albions glorious yle;</l>
               <l>And ſince then baniſht from a louely ſight,</l>
               <l>I maried haue my mind to ſad conceits,</l>
               <l>Though to the furtheſt part that fame dilates,</l>
               <l>I might on <hi>Pegaſus</hi> addreſſe my flight;</l>
               <l>Yet ſhould I ſtill whilſt I might breath or moue,</l>
               <l>Remaine the monſter of miſhap and loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sonet.</hi> 57.</head>
               <l>VVHilſt th'Apenin ſeems cloth'd with ſnows to vaunt,</l>
               <l>As if that their pure white all hues did ſtaine,</l>
               <l>I match them with thy matchleſſe faire againe,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe lillies haue a luſter, that they want:</l>
               <l>But when ſome die, train'd with a pleaſant ſhow,</l>
               <l>In their plaine-ſeeming depths, as many do,</l>
               <l>Then I remember how <hi>Aurora</hi> too,</l>
               <l>VVith louely rigor thouſands doth orethrow.</l>
               <l>Thus is it fatall by th'effects we know,</l>
               <l>That beautie muſt do harme, more then delight:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:29"/>
               <l>For lo the ſnow, the whiteſt of the white,</l>
               <l>Comes from the clouds, t'engender yce below:</l>
               <l>So ſhe with whom for beautie none compares,</l>
               <l>From clouds of cold diſdaine, raines downe deſpaires.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sonet.</hi> 58.</head>
               <l>FEare not, my Faire, that euer any chaunce</l>
               <l>So ſhake the reſolutions of my mind,</l>
               <l>That like <hi>Demophon</hi> changing with the wind,</l>
               <l>I thy fames rent not labor to enhaunce:</l>
               <l>The ring which thou in ſigne of fauour gaue,</l>
               <l>Shall from fine gold transforme it ſelfe in glaſſe:</l>
               <l>The Diamond which then ſo ſolid was,</l>
               <l>Soft like the waxe, each image ſhall receiue:</l>
               <l>Firſt ſhall each riuer turne vnto the ſpring,</l>
               <l>The talleſt Oke ſtand trembling like a reed,</l>
               <l>Harts in the aire, Whales on the mountaines feed,</l>
               <l>And foule confuſions ſeaze on euery thing;</l>
               <l>Before that I begin to change in ought,</l>
               <l>Or on another but beſtow one thought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 59.</head>
               <l>WHilſt euery youth to entertaine his loue,</l>
               <l>Did ſtraine his wits as farre as they might reach,</l>
               <l>And arming paſſions with a pow'rfull ſpeach,</l>
               <l>Vſde each patheticke phraſe that ſeru'd to moue:</l>
               <l>Then to ſome corner ſtill retir'd alone,</l>
               <l>I, whom melancholly from mirth did leade,</l>
               <l>As hauing view'd <hi>Meduſaes</hi> ſnakie head,</l>
               <l>Seem'd metamorphos'd in a marble ſtone:</l>
               <l>And as that wretched mirrour of miſchiefe,</l>
               <l>Whom earſt <hi>Apollo</hi> ſpoil'd, doth ſtill ſhed teares,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:30"/>
               <l>And in a ſtone the badge of ſorrow beares,</l>
               <l>While as a humid vapor ſhewes her griefe:</l>
               <l>So whilſt transform'd as in a ſtone I ſtay,</l>
               <l>A firie ſmoke doth blow my griefe away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 60.</head>
               <l>THe heauens beheld that all men did deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>That which the owner from the graue acquites,</l>
               <l>That ſleepe, the belly, and ſome baſe delights,</l>
               <l>Had baniſh'd vertue from beneath the skies;</l>
               <l>Which to the world againe for to reſtore,</l>
               <l>The gods did one of theirs, to th'earth transferre,</l>
               <l>And with as many bleſſings following her,</l>
               <l>As earſt <hi>Pandora</hi> kept of plagues in ſtore.</l>
               <l>She ſince ſhe came within this wretched vale,</l>
               <l>Doth in each mind a loue of glorie breed;</l>
               <l>Bettering the better parts that haue moſt need,</l>
               <l>And ſhewes how worldlings to the clouds may ſcale:</l>
               <l>She cleares the world, but ah hath darkned me,</l>
               <l>Made blind by her, my ſelfe I cannot ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 61.</head>
               <l>HOw long ſhall I beſtow my time in vaine,</l>
               <l>And ſound the praiſes of that ſpitefull boy;</l>
               <l>Who whilſt that I for him my paines imploy,</l>
               <l>Doth guerdon me with bondage and diſdaine?</l>
               <l>O, but for this I muſt his glorie raiſe,</l>
               <l>Since one thats worthie triumphs of my fall;</l>
               <l>Where great men oft of ſuch haue bene made thrall,</l>
               <l>Whoſe birth was baſe, whoſe beautie without praiſe.</l>
               <l>And yet in this his hatred doth appeare,</l>
               <l>For otherwiſe I might my loſſe repaire.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:30"/>
               <l>But being as ſhe is exceeding faire,</l>
               <l>I'm forc'd to hold one that's vngratefull deare:</l>
               <l>Theſe euerchanging thoughts which nought can bind,</l>
               <l>May well beare witneſſe of a troubled mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 62.</head>
               <l>WHen as the Sunne doth drinke vp all the ſtreames,</l>
               <l>And with a feruent heate the flowres doth kill;</l>
               <l>The ſhadow of a wood, or of a hill,</l>
               <l>Doth ſerue vs for a targe againſt his beames:</l>
               <l>But ah, thoſe eyes that burne me with deſire,</l>
               <l>And ſeeke to parch the ſubſtance of my ſoule,</l>
               <l>The ardour of their rayes for to controule,</l>
               <l>I wot not where my ſelfe for to retire:</l>
               <l>Twixt them and me, to haue procur'd ſome eaſe,</l>
               <l>I interpos'd the ſeas, woods, hils, and riuers;</l>
               <l>And yet am of thoſe neuer emptied quiuers,</l>
               <l>The obiect ſtill, and burne, be where I pleaſe:</l>
               <l>But of the cauſe I need not for to doubt,</l>
               <l>Within my breſt I beare the fire about.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 63.</head>
               <l>OFt haue I heard, which now I muſt deny,</l>
               <l>That nought can laſt if that it be extreame,</l>
               <l>Times dayly change, and we likewiſe in them,</l>
               <l>Things out of ſight do ſtraight forgotten die:</l>
               <l>There is nothing more vehement then loue,</l>
               <l>And yet I burne, and burne ſtill with one flame.</l>
               <l>Times oft haue chang'd, yet I remaine the ſame.</l>
               <l>Nought from my mind her image can remoue:</l>
               <l>The greatneſſe of my loue aſpires to ruth,</l>
               <l>Time vowes to crowne my conſtancie in th'end,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:31"/>
               <l>And abſence doth my fancies but extend;</l>
               <l>Thus I perceiue the Poet ſpake the truth,</l>
               <l>That who to ſee ſtrange countries were inclin'd,</l>
               <l>Might change the aire, but neuer change the mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 64.</head>
               <l>I Wot not what ſtrange things I haue deſign'd,</l>
               <l>But all my geſtures do preſage no good;</l>
               <l>My lookes are gaſtly-like, thoughts are my food,</l>
               <l>A ſilent pauſing ſhewes my troubled mind:</l>
               <l>Huge hoſts of thoughts are muſtring in my breſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſtrongeſt are conducted by deſpaire,</l>
               <l>Which haue inuolu'd my hopes in ſuch a ſnare,</l>
               <l>That I by death would ſeeke an endles reſt.</l>
               <l>What Furie in my breſt ſtrange cares enroules,</l>
               <l>And in the ſame would reare ſterne <hi>Plutoes</hi> ſeate!</l>
               <l>Go get you hence to the Tartarian gate,</l>
               <l>And breed ſuch terrors in the damned ſoules:</l>
               <l>Too many grieuous plagues my ſtate extorſe,</l>
               <l>Though apprehended horrors boſt not worſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Song</hi> 7.</head>
               <l>O Memorable day, that chanc'd to ſee</l>
               <l>A world of louing wonders ſtrangely wrought,</l>
               <l>Deepe in my breſt engrau'd by many a thought,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt be celebrated ſtill by me:</l>
               <l>And if that <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſo benigne will be,</l>
               <l>That happie happie place,</l>
               <l>Whereas that diuine face</l>
               <l>Did diſtribute ſuch grace,</l>
               <l>By pilgrims once as ſacred ſhall be ſought.</l>
               <l>When ſhe whom I a long time haue affected,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:31"/>
               <l>Amongſt the flowres went forth to take the aire;</l>
               <l>They being proud of ſuch a gueſts repaire,</l>
               <l>Though by her garments diuers times deiected,</l>
               <l>To gaze on her againe themſelues erected;</l>
               <l>Then ſoftly ſeem'd to ſay:</l>
               <l>O happie we this day;</l>
               <l>Our worthleſſe dew it may,</l>
               <l>Waſhing her feete with <hi>Nectar</hi> now compare.</l>
               <l>The Roſes did the roſie hue enuy,</l>
               <l>Of thoſe ſweet lips that did the Bees deceaue,</l>
               <l>That colour oft the Lillies wiſh'd to haue,</l>
               <l>Which did the Alablaſter piller die,</l>
               <l>On which all beauties glorie did rely;</l>
               <l>Her breath ſo ſweetly ſmell'd,</l>
               <l>The Violets as excell'd,</l>
               <l>To looke downe were compell'd;</l>
               <l>And ſo confeſt what foile they did receaue.</l>
               <l>I heard at leſt, loue made it ſo appeare,</l>
               <l>The fethered flockes her praiſes did proclaime:</l>
               <l>She whom the tyrant <hi>Tereus</hi> put to ſhame,</l>
               <l>Did leaue ſad plaints, and learn'd to praiſe my deare:</l>
               <l>To ioyne with her ſweet breath the winds drew neare;</l>
               <l>They were in loue no doubt,</l>
               <l>For circling her about,</l>
               <l>Their fancies burſted out,</l>
               <l>Whilſt all their ſounds ſeem'd but to ſound her name.</l>
               <l>There I mine eyes with pleaſant ſighes did cloy,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſeuerall parts in vaine I ſtriue t'vnfold;</l>
               <l>My faire was fairer many a thouſand fold</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Venus,</hi> when ſhe woo'd the baſhfull boy:</l>
               <l>This I remember both with griefe and ioy,</l>
               <l>Each of her lookes a dart,</l>
               <l>Might well haue kill'd a hart:</l>
               <l>Mine from my breſt did part,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:32"/>
               <l>And thence retir'd it to a ſweeter hold.</l>
               <l>Whilſt in her boſome whiles ſhe plac'd a flowre,</l>
               <l>Straight of the ſame I enuy would the caſe,</l>
               <l>And wiſh'd my hand a flowre t'haue found like grace;</l>
               <l>Then when on her it rain'd ſome hapning howre,</l>
               <l>I wiſh'd like <hi>Ioue</hi> t'haue falne downe in a ſhowre:</l>
               <l>But when the flowres ſhe ſpred,</l>
               <l>To make her ſelfe a bed,</l>
               <l>And with her gowne them cled,</l>
               <l>A thouſand times I wiſh'd t'haue had their place.</l>
               <l>Thus whilſt that ſenſleſſe things that bliſſe attain'd,</l>
               <l>Which vnto me good iuſtice would adiudge,</l>
               <l>Behind a little buſh (O poore refuge)</l>
               <l>Fed with her face, I Lizard-like remain'd:</l>
               <l>Then from her eyes ſo ſweet a poiſon rain'd,</l>
               <l>That gladly drinking death,</l>
               <l>I was not mou'd to wrath,</l>
               <l>Though like t'haue loſt my breath,</l>
               <l>Drown'd with the ſtreames of that moſt ſweet deluge.</l>
               <l>And might that happineſſe continue ſtill,</l>
               <l>Which did content me with ſo pleaſant ſights,</l>
               <l>My ſoule then rauiſh'd with moſt rare delights,</l>
               <l>With Ambroſie and Nectar I might fill:</l>
               <l>VVhich ah I feare, I ſurfeiting would kill.</l>
               <l>VVho would leaue off to thinke,</l>
               <l>To moue, to breath, or winke,</l>
               <l>But neuer irke to drinke</l>
               <l>The ſugred liquor that tranſports my ſprites?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 65.</head>
               <l>MY face the colours whiles of death diſplayes,</l>
               <l>And I who at my wretched ſtate repine,</l>
               <l>This mortall vaile would willingly reſigne,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:32"/>
               <l>And end my dole together with my dayes;</l>
               <l>But <hi>Cupid</hi> whom my danger muſt diſmayes,</l>
               <l>As loth to loſe one that decores his ſhrine,</l>
               <l>Straight in my breſt doth make <hi>Aurora</hi> ſhine,</l>
               <l>And by this ſtratageme my dying ſtayes.</l>
               <l>Then in mine eares he ſounds th'Angelike voice,</l>
               <l>And to my ſight preſents the beauteous face,</l>
               <l>And cals to mind that more then diuine grace,</l>
               <l>VVhich made me firſt for to confirme my choice:</l>
               <l>And I who all thoſe ſlights haue oft perceiu'd,</l>
               <l>Yet thus content my ſelfe to be deceiu'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sonet.</hi> 66.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> GO get thee heart from hence, for thou haſt prou'd</l>
               <l>The hatefull traitor that procur'd my fall.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>H.</hi> May I not yet once ſatisfie for all,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe loyaltie may make thee to be lou'd?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> Ile neuer truſt one that hath once betraid me:</l>
               <l>For once a traitor, and then neuer true.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>H.</hi> Yet would my wracke but make thee firſt to rue,</l>
               <l>That could truſt none if thou hadſt once diſmaid me.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>B.</hi> How euer others make me for to ſmart,</l>
               <l>I ſcorne to haue an enemie in my breſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>H.</hi> VVell, if that thou ſpoile me, Ile ſpoile thy reſt,</l>
               <l>VVant I a bodie, thou ſhalt want a heart:</l>
               <l>Thus do th'vnhappie ſtill augment their harmes,</l>
               <l>And thou haſt kild thy ſelfe with thine owne armes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 67.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> VVHat art thou, in ſuch ſort that wail'ſt thy fall,</l>
               <l>And comes ſurcharg'd with an exceſſiue griefe?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>H.</hi> A wofull wretch, that comes to craue releefe,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:33"/>
               <l>And was his heart that now hath none at all.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Why doſt thou thus to me vnfold thy ſtate,</l>
               <l>As if with thy miſhaps I would imbroile me,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>H.</hi> Becauſe the loue I bare to you did ſpoile me,</l>
               <l>And was the inſtrument of my hard fate:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And dare ſo baſe a wretch ſo high aſpire,</l>
               <l>As for to pleade for intereſt in my grace?</l>
               <l>Go get thee hence; or if thou do not ceaſe,</l>
               <l>I vow to burne thee with a greater fire:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>H.</hi> Ah, ah, this great vnkindnes ſtops my breath,</l>
               <l>Since thoſe that I loue beſt procure my death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 68.</head>
               <l>I Hope, I feare, reſolu'd, and yet I doubt,</l>
               <l>I'm cold as yce, and yet I burne as fire;</l>
               <l>I wot not what, and yet I much deſire,</l>
               <l>And trembling too, am deſperatly ſtout:</l>
               <l>Though melancholious wonders I deuiſe,</l>
               <l>And compaſſe much, yet nothing can embrace;</l>
               <l>And walke ore all, yet ſtand ſtill in one place,</l>
               <l>And bound on th'earth, do ſoare aboue the skies:</l>
               <l>I beg for life, and yet I bray for death,</l>
               <l>And haue a mightie courage, yet diſpaire;</l>
               <l>I euer muſe, yet am without all care,</l>
               <l>And ſhout aloud, yet neuer ſtraine my breath:</l>
               <l>I change as oft as any wind can do,</l>
               <l>Yet for all this am euer conſtant too.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 69.</head>
               <l>VVHat wonder though my count'nance be not bright,</l>
               <l>And that I looke as one with clouds inclos'd?</l>
               <l>A great part of th'earth is interpos'd</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:33"/>
               <l>Betwixt the Sunne and me that giues me light:</l>
               <l>Ah (ſince ſequeſtred from that diuine face)</l>
               <l>I find my ſelfe more ſluggiſhly diſpos'd:</l>
               <l>Nor whilſt on that cleare patterne I repos'd,</l>
               <l>That put my inward darkneſſe to the flight.</l>
               <l>No more then can the Sunne ſhine without beames,</l>
               <l>Can ſhe vncompas'd with her vertues liue,</l>
               <l>Which to the world an euidence do giue</l>
               <l>Of that rare worth which many a mouth proclaimes:</l>
               <l>And which ſometime did purifie my mind,</l>
               <l>That by the want thereof is now made blind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 70.</head>
               <l>SOme gallant ſprites whoſe waies none yet dare trace,</l>
               <l>To ſhew the world the wonders of their wit,</l>
               <l>Did (as their toſſed fancies thought moſt fit)</l>
               <l>Forme rare <hi>Idaeas</hi> of a diuine face.</l>
               <l>Yet neuer Art to that true worth attain'd,</l>
               <l>Which Nature now growne prodigall, imparts</l>
               <l>To one, deare one, whoſe ſacred ſeuerall parts,</l>
               <l>Are more admir'd then all that Poets fain'd.</l>
               <l>Thoſe bordring climes that boaſt of beauties ſhrine,</l>
               <l>If once thy ſight enrich'd their ſoiles (my loue:)</l>
               <l>Then all with one conſent behou'd t'approue,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Calidon</hi> doth beauties beſt confine.</l>
               <l>But ah, the heau'n on this my ruine ſounds,</l>
               <l>The more her worth, the deeper are my wounds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 71.</head>
               <l>FOr eyes that are deliuer'd of their birth,</l>
               <l>And hearts that can complaine, none needs to care:</l>
               <l>I pitie not their ſighes that pierce the ayre,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:34"/>
               <l>To weepe at will were a degree of mirth:</l>
               <l>But he (ay me) is to be pitied moſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſorrowes haue attain'd to that degree,</l>
               <l>That they are paſt expreſſing, and can be</l>
               <l>Onely imagin'd by a man that's loſt.</l>
               <l>The teares that would burſt out yet are reſtrain'd,</l>
               <l>Th'impriſon'd plaints that periſh without fame,</l>
               <l>Sighs form'd and ſmoother'd ere they get a name,</l>
               <l>Thoſe to be pitied are (ô griefe vnfain'd)</l>
               <l>Whilſt ſighes the voice, the voice the ſighs confounds,</l>
               <l>Then teares marre both, and all are out of bounds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 72.</head>
               <l>O My Deſire, if thou tookſt time to marke,</l>
               <l>When I againſt my will thy ſight forſooke:</l>
               <l>How that mine eyes with many an earneſt looke,</l>
               <l>Did in thy beauties depth themſelues embarke:</l>
               <l>And when our lippes did ſeale the laſt farewell,</l>
               <l>How loth were mine from thoſe delights to part.</l>
               <l>For what was purpos'd by the panting heart,</l>
               <l>My toung cleau'd to the throat, and could not tell.</l>
               <l>Then when to ſorrow I the raines enlarg'd,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt being ſpoil'd of comfort and of might,</l>
               <l>As forc'd for to forgo thy beauties light,</l>
               <l>Of burning ſighs a volley I diſcharg'd:</l>
               <l>No doubt then when thou ſpid'ſt what I did proue,</l>
               <l>Thou ſaidſt within thy ſelfe, <hi>This man doth loue.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Madr.</hi> 2.</head>
               <l>BEheld'ſt thou me looke backe at our goodnight:</l>
               <l>O no good night,</l>
               <l>Diſmall, obſcure and blacke:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:34"/>
               <l>Mine eyes then in their language ſpake,</l>
               <l>And would haue thus complain'd:</l>
               <l>Thou leau'ſt the hart, makes vs depart;</l>
               <l>Curſt is our part,</l>
               <l>And hard to be ſuſtain'd.</l>
               <l>O happie heart that was retain'd:</l>
               <l>Alas, to leaue vs too, there is no Art:</l>
               <l>It in her boſome now ſhould nightly ſleepe,</l>
               <l>And we exil'd, ſtill for her abſence weepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 73.</head>
               <l>WHen whiles thy daintie hand doth croſſe my light,</l>
               <l>It ſeemes an yuorie table for Loues ſtorie,</l>
               <l>On which th'impearled pillars, beauties glorie,</l>
               <l>Are rear'd betwixt the Sunne and my weake ſight.</l>
               <l>Though this would great humanitie appeare,</l>
               <l>Which for a litle while my flame allayes,</l>
               <l>And ſaues me vnconſum'd with beauties rayes,</l>
               <l>I rather die, then buy my life ſo deare.</l>
               <l>Oft haue I wiſh'd whil'ſt in this ſtate I was,</l>
               <l>That th'Alablaſter bulwarke might tranſpare,</l>
               <l>And that the pillars rarer then they are,</l>
               <l>Might whiles permit ſome hapning rayes to paſſe:</l>
               <l>But if Eclips'd thy beauties Sunne muſt ſtand,</l>
               <l>Then be it with the moone of thine owne hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 74.</head>
               <l>LO, in my Faire each of the Planets raignes:</l>
               <l>She is as <hi>Saturne,</hi> euer graue and wiſe,</l>
               <l>And as <hi>Ioues</hi> thunderbolts, her thundring eyes</l>
               <l>Do plague the pride of men with endleſſe paines:</l>
               <l>Her voyce is as <hi>Apollo's,</hi> and her head</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:35"/>
               <l>Is euer garniſh'd with his golden beames,</l>
               <l>And ô her heart, which neuer fancie tames:</l>
               <l>More fierce then <hi>Mars</hi> makes thouſands to lie dead.</l>
               <l>From <hi>Mercurie</hi> her eloquence proceeds,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Venus</hi> ſhe the ſweetneſſe doth retaine,</l>
               <l>Her face ſtill full doth <hi>Phoebe's</hi> lightneſſe ſtaine,</l>
               <l>Whom likewiſe ſhe in Chaſtitie exceeds.</l>
               <l>No wonder then though this in me doth moue,</l>
               <l>To ſuch a diuine ſoule, a diuine loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 75.</head>
               <l>MY faithfull thoughts no dutie do omit;</l>
               <l>But being fraughted with moſt zealous cares,</l>
               <l>Are euer buſied for my loues affaires,</l>
               <l>And in my breſt as Senators do ſit,</l>
               <l>To my hearts famine yeelding pleaſant food.</l>
               <l>They ſugred fancies in my boſome breed,</l>
               <l>And would haue all ſo well for to ſucceed,</l>
               <l>That through exceſſiue care they nought conclude:</l>
               <l>But ah, I feare that their affections trie</l>
               <l>In end like th'Apes, that whil'ſt he ſeekes to proue</l>
               <l>The powrefull motions of a parents loue,</l>
               <l>Doth oft embrace his young ones till they die:</l>
               <l>So to my heart my thoughts do cleaue ſo faſt,</l>
               <l>That ô, I feare they make it burſt at laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 76.</head>
               <l>WHat fortune ſtrange, what ſtrange misfortune erſt</l>
               <l>Did toſſe me with a thouſand things in vaine,</l>
               <l>Whiles ſad deſpaires confounded did remaine?</l>
               <l>Whiles all my hopes were to the winds diſperſt?</l>
               <l>Erected whiles, and whiles againe renuerſt?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:35"/>
               <l>Whiles nurc'd with ſmiles, whiles murther'd with diſdaine,</l>
               <l>Whiles borne aloft, whiles laid as low againe?</l>
               <l>And with what ſtate haue I not once bene verſt?</l>
               <l>But yet my conſtant mind which vertue binds,</l>
               <l>From the firſt courſe no new occurrence drawes:</l>
               <l>Still like a rocke by ſea againſt the waues,</l>
               <l>Or like a hill by land againſt the winds:</l>
               <l>So all the world that viewes that which I find,</l>
               <l>May damne my deſtinie, but not my mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 77.</head>
               <l>I Long to ſee this Pilgrimage expire,</l>
               <l>That makes the eyes for to enuie the mind,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſight with abſence cannot be confin'd,</l>
               <l>But warmes it ſelfe ſtill at thy beauties fire.</l>
               <l>Loue in my boſome did thy image ſinke</l>
               <l>So deepely once, it cannot be worne out:</l>
               <l>Yet once the eyes may haue their courſe about,</l>
               <l>And ſee farre more, then now the mind can thinke.</l>
               <l>Ile once retire in time before I die,</l>
               <l>There where thou firſt my libertie didſt ſpoile:</l>
               <l>For otherwiſe dead in a forraine ſoile,</l>
               <l>Still with my ſelfe entomb'd my faith ſhall lie.</l>
               <l>No, no, Ile rather die once in thy ſight,</l>
               <l>Then in this ſtate die ten times in one night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 78.</head>
               <l>I Chanc'd my deare to come vpon a day,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt thou waſt but ariſing from thy bed,</l>
               <l>And the warme ſnowes with comely garments cled;</l>
               <l>More rich then glorious, and more fine then gay:</l>
               <l>Then bluſhing to be ſeene in ſuch a caſe,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:36"/>
               <l>O how thy curled lockes mine eyes did pleaſe,</l>
               <l>And well become thoſe waues, thy beauties ſeas,</l>
               <l>Which by thy haires were fram'd vpon thy face:</l>
               <l>Such was <hi>Diana</hi> once when being ſpide</l>
               <l>By raſh <hi>Acteon,</hi> ſhe was much commou'd:</l>
               <l>Yet more diſcreet then th'angrie goddeſſe prou'd,</l>
               <l>Thou knew'ſt I came through error, not of pride:</l>
               <l>And thought the wounds I got by thy ſweet ſight,</l>
               <l>Were too great ſcourges for a fault ſo light.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Madr.</hi> 3.</head>
               <l>I Saw my Loue like <hi>Cupids</hi> mother,</l>
               <l>Her treſſes ſporting with her face,</l>
               <l>Which being proud of ſuch a grace;</l>
               <l>Whiles kiſt th'one cheeke, and whiles the other:</l>
               <l>Her eyes glad ſuch a meanes t'embrace,</l>
               <l>Whereby they might haue me betraid,</l>
               <l>Themſelues they in ambuſhment laid,</l>
               <l>Behind the treaſures of her haire,</l>
               <l>And wounded me ſo deadly there:</l>
               <l>That doubtleſſe I had dead remain'd,</l>
               <l>Were not the treaſon ſhe diſdain'd;</l>
               <l>And with her lippes ſweet balme my health procur'd:</l>
               <l>I would be wounded oft to be ſo cur'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Madr.</hi> 4.</head>
               <l>ONce for her face, I ſaw my Faire</l>
               <l>Did of her haires a ſhadow make:</l>
               <l>Or rather wandring hearts to take.</l>
               <l>She ſtented had thoſe nets of gold,</l>
               <l>Sure by this meanes all men t'enſnare,</l>
               <l>She toſs'd the ſtreamers with her breath,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:36"/>
               <l>And ſeem'd to boaſt a world with death:</l>
               <l>But when I did the ſleight behold,</l>
               <l>I to the ſhadow did repaire,</l>
               <l>To flie the burning of thine eyes;</l>
               <l>O happie he, by ſuch a ſleight that dies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 79.</head>
               <l>THe moſt refreſhing waters come from rockes,</l>
               <l>Some bitter rootes oft ſend foorth daintie flowres,</l>
               <l>The growing greenes are cheriſhed with ſhowres,</l>
               <l>And pleaſant ſtemmes ſpring from deformed ſtockes:</l>
               <l>The hardeſt hils do feed the faireſt flockes:</l>
               <l>All greateſt ſweetes were ſugred firſt with ſowres,</l>
               <l>The headleſſe courſe of vncontrolled houres,</l>
               <l>To all difficulties a way vnlockes.</l>
               <l>I hope to haue a heauen within thine armes,</l>
               <l>And quiet calmes when all theſe ſtormes are paſt,</l>
               <l>Which coming vnexpected at the laſt,</l>
               <l>May burie in Obliuion by-gone harmes.</l>
               <l>To ſuffer firſt, to ſorrow, ſigh, and ſmart,</l>
               <l>Endeeres the conqueſt of a cruell hart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 80.</head>
               <l>WHen Loue ſpide death like to triumph ore me,</l>
               <l>That had bene ſuch a pillar of his throne;</l>
               <l>And that all <hi>AEſculapius</hi> hopes were gone,</l>
               <l>Whoſe drugs had not the force to ſet me free,</l>
               <l>He labour'd to reduce the Fates decree,</l>
               <l>And thus beſpake the tyrant that ſpares none:</l>
               <l>Thou that waſt neuer mou'd with worldlings mone,</l>
               <l>To ſaue this man for my requeſt agree:</l>
               <l>And I proteſt that he ſhall dearely buy</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:37"/>
               <l>The ſhort prolonging of a wretched life:</l>
               <l>For it ſhall be inuolu'd in ſuch a ſtrife,</l>
               <l>That he ſhall neuer liue, but euer die.</l>
               <l>O what a cruell kindneſſe <hi>Cupid</hi> crau'd,</l>
               <l>Who for to kill me oft, my life once ſau'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 81.</head>
               <l>OFt haue I vow'd of none t'attend releefe,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ardour was not equall vnto mine,</l>
               <l>And in whoſe face there did not clearely ſhine,</l>
               <l>The very image of my inward greefe:</l>
               <l>But ſo the deſt'nies do my thoughts diſpoſe,</l>
               <l>I wot not what a fatall force ordaines,</l>
               <l>That I abaſe my ſelfe to beare diſdaines,</l>
               <l>And honour one that ruines my repoſe.</l>
               <l>Oft haue I vow'd no more to be orethrowne,</l>
               <l>But ſtill retaining my affections free,</l>
               <l>To fancie none, but them that fancied me:</l>
               <l>But now I ſee my will is not mine owne.</l>
               <l>Then ah, may you bewitch my iudgement ſo,</l>
               <l>That I muſt loue, although my heart ſay no!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 82.</head>
               <l>I Rage to ſee ſome in the ſcroules of fame,</l>
               <l>Whoſe louers wits more rare then their deſerts,</l>
               <l>Do make them prais'd for many gallant parts,</l>
               <l>The which doth make themſelues to bluſh for ſhame:</l>
               <l>Where thou whom euen thine enemies cannot blame,</l>
               <l>Though famous in the center of all hearts;</l>
               <l>Yet to the world thy worth no pen imparts:</l>
               <l>Which iuſtly might thoſe wrong-ſpent praiſes claime.</l>
               <l>But what vaine pen ſo fondly durſt aſpire,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:37"/>
               <l>To paint that worth which ſoares aboue each wit,</l>
               <l>Which hardly higheſt apprehenſions hit,</l>
               <l>Not to be told, but thought of with deſire:</l>
               <l>For where the ſubiect doth ſurmount the ſence,</l>
               <l>We beſt by ſilence ſhew a great pretence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Song.</hi> 8.</head>
               <l>I would thy beauties wonders ſhow,</l>
               <l>Which none can tell, yet all do know:</l>
               <l>Thou borrowes nought to moue delight,</l>
               <l>Thy beauties (Deare) are all perfite.</l>
               <l>And at the head Ile firſt begin,</l>
               <l>Moſt rich without, more rich within:</l>
               <l>Within a place <hi>Minerua</hi> claimes,</l>
               <l>Without, <hi>Apollo's</hi> golden beames,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſmiling waues thoſe ſeas may ſcorne,</l>
               <l>Where Beauties goddeſſe earſt was borne:</l>
               <l>And yet do boaſt a world with death,</l>
               <l>If toſs'd with gales of thy ſweet breath.</l>
               <l>I for two creſcents take thy browes,</l>
               <l>Or rather for two bended bowes,</l>
               <l>Whoſe archer loue, whoſe white mens harts,</l>
               <l>Thy frownes, no, ſmiles, ſmiles are thy darts;</l>
               <l>Which to my ruine euer bent,</l>
               <l>Are oft diſcharg'd but neuer ſpent.</l>
               <l>Thy ſunnes, I dare not ſay, thine eyes,</l>
               <l>Which oft do ſet, and oft do riſe:</l>
               <l>Whilſt in thy faces heau'n they moue,</l>
               <l>Giue light to all the world of loue:</l>
               <l>And yet do whiles defraud our ſight,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt two white clouds eclipſe their light.</l>
               <l>The laborinthes of thine eares,</l>
               <l>VVhere Beautie both her colours reares,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:38"/>
               <l>Are lawne laid on a ſcarlet ground,</l>
               <l>Whereas Loues ecchoes euer ſound:</l>
               <l>Thy cheekes, ſtrawberries dipt in milke,</l>
               <l>As white as ſnow, as ſoft as ſilke;</l>
               <l>Gardens of lillies and of roſes,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Cupid</hi> ſtill himſelfe repoſes,</l>
               <l>And on their daintie rounds he ſits,</l>
               <l>When he would charme the rareſt wits.</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſwelling vales which beautie owes,</l>
               <l>Are parted with a dike of ſnowes:</l>
               <l>The line that ſtill is ſtretch'd out euen,</l>
               <l>And doth deuide thy faces heauen:</l>
               <l>It hath the proſpect of thoſe lippes,</l>
               <l>From which no word vnballanc'd ſlippes:</l>
               <l>There is a grot by Nature fram'd,</l>
               <l>Which Art to follow is aſham'd:</l>
               <l>All thoſe whom fame for rare giues foorth,</l>
               <l>Compar'd with this are litle woorth,</l>
               <l>T'is all with pearles and rubies ſet;</l>
               <l>But I the beſt almoſt forget,</l>
               <l>There do the gods (as I haue tride)</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Ambroſie</hi> and <hi>Nectar</hi> hide.</l>
               <l>The daintie pot that's in thy chin,</l>
               <l>Makes many a heart for to fall in,</l>
               <l>Whereas they boyle with pleaſant fires,</l>
               <l>Whoſe fuell is enflam'd Deſires.</l>
               <l>T'is eminent in Beauties field,</l>
               <l>As that which threatens all to yeeld.</l>
               <l>T'vphold thoſe treaſures vndefac'd,</l>
               <l>There is an yuorie pillar plac'd,</l>
               <l>Which like to <hi>Maias</hi> ſonne doth proue,</l>
               <l>For to beare vp this world of loue:</l>
               <l>In it ſome branched veines ariſe,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:38"/>
               <l>As th'azure pure would braue the skies.</l>
               <l>I ſee whiles as I downward moue,</l>
               <l>Two litle globes, two worlds of loue,</l>
               <l>Which vndiſcouer'd, vndiſtreſſed,</l>
               <l>Were neuer with no burden preſſed:</l>
               <l>Nor will for Lord acknowledge none,</l>
               <l>To be enſtal'd in Beauties throne:</l>
               <l>As barren yet ſo were they bare,</l>
               <l>O happie he that might dwell there.</l>
               <l>And now my Muſe we muſt make haſt,</l>
               <l>To it that's iuſtly cal'd the waſt,</l>
               <l>That waſts my heart with hopes and feares,</l>
               <l>My breath with ſighes, mine eyes with teares:</l>
               <l>Yet I to it for all thoſe harmes,</l>
               <l>Would make a girdle of mine armes.</l>
               <l>There is below which no man knowes,</l>
               <l>A mountaine made of naked ſnowes;</l>
               <l>Amidſt the which is Loues great ſeale,</l>
               <l>To which for helpe I oft appeale,</l>
               <l>And if by it my right were paſt,</l>
               <l>I ſhould brooke beautie ſtill at laſt.</l>
               <l>But ah, my Muſe will loſe the Crowne,</l>
               <l>I dare not go no further downe,</l>
               <l>Which doth diſcourage me ſo much,</l>
               <l>That I no other thing will touch.</l>
               <l>No not thoſe litle daintie feet,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Thetis</hi> ſtaine, for <hi>Venus</hi> meet:</l>
               <l>Thus wading through the depths of Beautie,</l>
               <l>I would haue faine diſcharg'd my dutie:</l>
               <l>Yet doth thy worth ſo paſſe my skill,</l>
               <l>That I ſhew nothing but good will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 83.</head>
               <l>THat fault on me (my Faire) no further vrge,</l>
               <l>Nor wreſt it not vnto a crooked ſence,</l>
               <l>The puniſhment elſe paffeth the offence:</l>
               <l>This fault was in it ſelfe too great a ſcourge,</l>
               <l>Since I behoou'd to giue th'occaſion place,</l>
               <l>And could not haue the meanes to viſite thee.</l>
               <l>Could there haue come a greater croſſe to me,</l>
               <l>Then ſo to be ſequeſtred from thy face?</l>
               <l>And yet I thinke that fortune for my reſt,</l>
               <l>Though for the time it did turmoile my mind</l>
               <l>Admit ſhe be (as many call her) blind,</l>
               <l>Did for the time then ſtumble on the beſt.</l>
               <l>To looke vpon thine eyes had I preſum'd,</l>
               <l>I might haue reſted by their rayes conſum'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 84.</head>
               <l>AH thou (my Loue) wilt loſe thy ſelfe at laſt,</l>
               <l>VVho can to match thy ſelfe with none agree:</l>
               <l>Thou ow'ſt thy father Nephewes, and to me</l>
               <l>A recompence for all my paſſions paſt.</l>
               <l>Ah, why ſhould'ſt thou thy beauties treaſure waſt,</l>
               <l>VVhich will begin for to decay I ſee?</l>
               <l>Earſt <hi>Daphne</hi> did become a barren tree,</l>
               <l>Becauſe ſhe was not halfe ſo wiſe as chaſt:</l>
               <l>And all the faireſt things do ſooneſt fade,</l>
               <l>VVhich O, I feare thou with repentance trie;</l>
               <l>The roſes blaſted are the lillies dye,</l>
               <l>And all do languiſh in the ſommers ſhade:</l>
               <l>Yet will I grieue to ſee thoſe flowers fall downe,</l>
               <l>VVhich for my temples ſhould haue fram'd a crowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 85.</head>
               <l>SOme yet not borne ſurueying lines of mine,</l>
               <l>Shall enuie with a ſigh, the eyes that view'd</l>
               <l>Thoſe beauties with my bloud ſo oft imbrude,</l>
               <l>The which by me in many a part do ſhine.</l>
               <l>Thoſe reliques then of this turmoil'd engine,</l>
               <l>VVhich for thy fauour haue ſo long purſude,</l>
               <l>Then after death will make my fortune rued,</l>
               <l>And thee deſpited that didſt make me pine.</l>
               <l>Ah, that thou ſhould'ſt, to wracke ſo many hearts,</l>
               <l>Exceed in all excellencies, but loue!</l>
               <l>That maske of rigour from thy mind remoue,</l>
               <l>And then thou art accompliſh'd in all parts:</l>
               <l>Then ſhall thy fame ore all vntainted flie,</l>
               <l>Thou in my lines, and I ſhall liue in thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Song.</hi> 9.</head>
               <l>O Happie <hi>Tithon,</hi> if thou know'ſt thy hap,</l>
               <l>And value thy wealth, but as I do my want,</l>
               <l>Then need'ſt thou not (which (ah) I grieue to grant)</l>
               <l>Repine at <hi>Ioue,</hi> lull'd in his lemmans lap:</l>
               <l>That golden ſhower in which he did repoſe,</l>
               <l>One dewie drop it ſtaines,</l>
               <l>VVhich thy <hi>Aurora</hi> raines</l>
               <l>Vpon the rurall plaines,</l>
               <l>VVhen from thy bed ſhe paſſionatly goes.</l>
               <l>Then wakened with the muſicke of the Mearles,</l>
               <l>She not remembers <hi>Memnon</hi> when ſhe mournes:</l>
               <l>That faithfull flame which in her boſome burnes,</l>
               <l>From chriſtall conduits throwes thoſe liquide pearles.</l>
               <l>Sad from thy ſight ſo ſoone to be remou'd,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:40"/>
               <l>She ſo her griefe delates,</l>
               <l>O fauor'd by the fates,</l>
               <l>Aboue the happieſt ſtates,</l>
               <l>Who art of one ſo worthie well belou'd.</l>
               <l>This is not ſhe that onely ſhines by night,</l>
               <l>No borrow'd beame doth beautifie thy Faire:</l>
               <l>But this is ſhe, whoſe beauties more then rare,</l>
               <l>Come crown'd with roſes to reſtore the light,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Phoebe</hi> pitch'd her pitchie pauilion out,</l>
               <l>The world with weeping told,</l>
               <l>How happie it would hold</l>
               <l>It ſelfe, but to behold</l>
               <l>The azure pale that compas'd her about.</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt like a palide half-impriſon'd roſe,</l>
               <l>Whoſe naked white doth but to bluſh begin,</l>
               <l>A litle ſcarlet deckes the yuorie skinne,</l>
               <l>Which ſtill doth glance tranſparent as ſhe goes:</l>
               <l>The beamie god comes burning with deſire;</l>
               <l>And when he finds her gone,</l>
               <l>With many a grieuous grone,</l>
               <l>Enrag'd, remounts anone,</l>
               <l>And threatneth all our Hemi-ſphaere with fire.</l>
               <l>Lift vp thine eyes and but behold thy bliſſe,</l>
               <l>Th'heau'ns raine their riches on thee whil'ſt thou ſleep'ſt:</l>
               <l>Thinke what a matchleſſe treaſure that thou keep'ſt,</l>
               <l>When thou haſt all that any elſe can wiſh.</l>
               <l>Thoſe Sunnes which daily dazle thy dim eyes,</l>
               <l>Might with one beame or ſo,</l>
               <l>Which thou mightſt well forgo,</l>
               <l>Straight baniſh all my wo,</l>
               <l>And make me all the world for to deſpiſe.</l>
               <l>But Sun-parch'd people loath the precious ſtones,</l>
               <l>And through abundance vilifie the gold;</l>
               <l>All diſ-eſteeme the treaſures that they hold,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:40"/>
               <l>And thinke not things poſſeſt (as they thought) once.</l>
               <l>Who ſurfet oft on ſuch exceſſiue ioyes,</l>
               <l>Can neuer pleaſure prize,</l>
               <l>But building on the skies,</l>
               <l>All preſent things deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>And like their treaſure leſſe, then others toyes.</l>
               <l>I enuie not thy bliſſe, ſo heau'n hath doom'd;</l>
               <l>And yet I cannot but lament mine owne,</l>
               <l>Whoſe hopes hard at the harueſt were orethrowne,</l>
               <l>And bliſſe halfe ripe, with froſts of feare conſum'd:</l>
               <l>Faire bloſſomes, which of fairer fruites did boaſt,</l>
               <l>Were blaſted in the flowers,</l>
               <l>With eye-exacted ſhowers,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſweet-ſuppoſed ſowers</l>
               <l>Of preconceited pleaſures grieu'd me moſt.</l>
               <l>And what a griefe is this (as chance effects)</l>
               <l>To ſee the rareſt beauties worſt beſtow'd?</l>
               <l>Ah, why ſhould halting <hi>Vulcan</hi> be made proud</l>
               <l>Of that great beautie which ſterne <hi>Mars</hi> affects?</l>
               <l>And why ſhould <hi>Tithon</hi> thus, whoſe day growes late,</l>
               <l>Enioy the mornings loue?</l>
               <l>Which though that I diſproue,</l>
               <l>Yet will I too approue,</l>
               <l>Since that it is her will, and my hard fate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>An Eccho.</head>
               <l>AH, will no ſoule giue eare vnto my mone? <hi>one</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who anſwers thus ſo kindly when I crie? <hi>I</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What foſtred thee that pities my deſpaire? <hi>aire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou blabbing gueſt, what know'ſt thou of my fall? <hi>all</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What did I when I firſt my Faire diſclos'd? <hi>los'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where was my reaſon, that it would not doubt? <hi>out</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What canſt thou tell me of my Ladies will? <hi>ill</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:41"/>
               <l>VVherewith can ſhe acquit my loyall part? <hi>art</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhat hath ſhe then with me to diſaguiſe? <hi>a guiſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhat haue I done, ſince ſhe gainſt loue repin'd? <hi>pin'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhat did I when I her to life prefer'd? <hi>er'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhat did mine eyes, whil'ſt ſhe my heart reſtrain'd? <hi>rain'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhat did ſhe whil'ſt my muſe her praiſe proclaim'd? <hi>claimd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And what? and how? this doth me moſt affright. <hi>of right</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhat if I neuer ſue to her againe? <hi>gaine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And what when all my paſſions are repreſt? <hi>reſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But what thing will beſt ſerue t'aſſwage deſire? <hi>ire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And what will ſerue to mitigate my rage? <hi>age</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I ſee the Sunne begins for to deſcend. <hi>end</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 87.</head>
               <l>NO wonder, thou endang'reſt liues with lookes,</l>
               <l>And doſt bewitch the boſome by the eare:</l>
               <l>VVhat hoſtes of hearts, that no ſuch ſleight did feare,</l>
               <l>Are now entangled by thy beauties hookes?</l>
               <l>But if ſo many to the world approue,</l>
               <l>Thoſe princely vertues that enrich my mind,</l>
               <l>And hold thee for the honour of thy kind;</l>
               <l>Yea though diſdain'd, yet deſperatly loue:</l>
               <l>O what a world of hapleſſe louers liue,</l>
               <l>That like a treaſure entertaine their thought,</l>
               <l>And ſeeme in ſhow as if affecting nought,</l>
               <l>And in their breſt t'entombe their fancies ſtriue:</l>
               <l>Yet let not this with pride thy heart poſſeſſe;</l>
               <l>The Sun being mounted high, doth ſeeme the leſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 88.</head>
               <l>THoſe beauties (Deare) which all thy ſexe enuies,</l>
               <l>As grieu'd men ſhould ſuch ſacred wonders view:</l>
               <l>For pompe apparel'd in a purple hue,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:41"/>
               <l>Do whiles diſdaine the pride of mortall eyes,</l>
               <l>VVhich ah attempting farre aboue their might,</l>
               <l>Do gaze vpon the glorie of thoſe Sunnes,</l>
               <l>Whilſt many a ray that from their brightneſſe runnes,</l>
               <l>Doth dazle all that dare looke on their light:</l>
               <l>Or was it this, which ô I feare me moſt,</l>
               <l>That cled with ſcarlet, ſo thy pureſt parts,</l>
               <l>Thy face it hauing wounded worlds of harts,</l>
               <l>Would die her Lillies with the bloud they loſt:</l>
               <l>Thus ere thy cruelties were long conceal'd,</l>
               <l>They by thy guiltie bluſh would be reueal'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 89.</head>
               <l>SMall comfort might my baniſh'd hopes recall,</l>
               <l>When whiles my daintie faire I ſighing ſee;</l>
               <l>If I could thinke that one were ſhed for me,</l>
               <l>It were a guerdon great enough for all:</l>
               <l>Or would ſhe let one teare of pittie fall,</l>
               <l>That ſeem'd diſmiſt from a remorcefnll eye,</l>
               <l>I could content my ſelfe vngrieu'd to die,</l>
               <l>And nothing might my conſtancie appall,</l>
               <l>The onely ſound of that ſweet word of loue,</l>
               <l>Preſt twixt thoſe lips that do my doome containe,</l>
               <l>Were I imbark'd, might me backe againe</l>
               <l>From death to life, and make me breath and moue.</l>
               <l>Strange crueltie, that neuer can afford</l>
               <l>So much as once one ſigh, one teare, one word.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 90.</head>
               <l>I Wot not what tranſported hath my mind,</l>
               <l>That I in armes againſt a goddeſſe ſtand;</l>
               <l>Yet though I ſue t'one of th'immortall band,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:42"/>
               <l>The like before was proſp'rouſly deſign'd.</l>
               <l>To loue <hi>Anchiſes Venus</hi> thought no ſcorne,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Thetis</hi> earſt was with a mortall match'd,</l>
               <l>Whom if th'aſpiring <hi>Peleus</hi> had not catch'd,</l>
               <l>The great <hi>Achilles</hi> neuer had bene borne.</l>
               <l>Thus flatter I my ſelfe whilſt nought confines.</l>
               <l>My wandring fancies that ſtrange wayes do trace;</l>
               <l>He that embrac'd a cloud in <hi>Iunoes</hi> place,</l>
               <l>May be a terror to the like deſignes:</l>
               <l>But fame in end th'aduentrer euer crownes,</l>
               <l>Whom either th'iſſue or th'attempt renownes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 91.</head>
               <l>ANd muſt I loſe in vaine ſo great a loue,</l>
               <l>And build thy glorie on my ruin'd ſtate?</l>
               <l>And can a heauenly breſt contract ſuch hate?</l>
               <l>And is the mildeſt ſexe ſo hard to moue?</l>
               <l>Haue all my offrings had no greater force,</l>
               <l>The which ſo oft haue made thine altars ſmoke?</l>
               <l>Well, if that thou haue vow'd not to reuoke</l>
               <l>The fatall doome that's farre from all remorce,</l>
               <l>For the laſt ſacrifice my ſelfe ſhall ſmart,</l>
               <l>My bloud muſt quench my vehement deſires;</l>
               <l>And let thine eyes drinke vp my funerall fires,</l>
               <l>And with my aſhes glut thy Tygriſh heart:</l>
               <l>So though thou at my wonted flames didſt ſpurne,</l>
               <l>Thou muſt truſt thoſe, when as thou ſeeſt me burne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 92.</head>
               <l>I Wot not which to chalenge for my death,</l>
               <l>Of thoſe thy beauties that my ruine ſeekes,</l>
               <l>The pure white fingers or the daintie cheekes,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:42"/>
               <l>The golden treſſes, or the Nectard breath:</l>
               <l>Ah they be all too guiltie of my fall,</l>
               <l>All wounded me though I their glorie rais'd;</l>
               <l>Although I graunt they need not to be prais'd,</l>
               <l>It may ſuffiſe they be <hi>Auroraes</hi> all:</l>
               <l>Yet for all this, O moſt ingratefull woman,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt not ſcape the ſcourge of iuſt diſdaine;</l>
               <l>I gaue thee gifts thou ſhouldſt haue giuen againe,</l>
               <l>It's ſhame to be in thy inferiors common:</l>
               <l>I gaue all what I held moſt deare to thee,</l>
               <l>Yet to this houre thou neuer guerdon'd me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 93.</head>
               <l>VVHilſt careleſſe ſwimming in thy beauties ſeas,</l>
               <l>I wondring was at that bewitching grace,</l>
               <l>Thou painted pitie on a cruell face,</l>
               <l>And angled ſo my iudgement by mine eyes:</l>
               <l>But now begun to triumph in my ſcorne,</l>
               <l>When I cannot retire my ſteps againe,</l>
               <l>Thou arm'ſt thine eyes with enuy and diſdaine,</l>
               <l>To murther my abortiue hopes halfe borne:</l>
               <l>Whilſt like to end this long continued ſtrife,</l>
               <l>My paleneſſe ſhewes I periſh in diſpaire;</l>
               <l>Thou loth to loſe one that eſteemes thee faire,</l>
               <l>With ſome ſweete word or looke prolongſt my life:</l>
               <l>And ſo each day in doubt redact'ſt my ſtate,</l>
               <l>Deare do not ſo, once either loue or hate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 94.</head>
               <l>MIne eyes would euer on thy beauties gaze,</l>
               <l>Mine eares are euer greedie of thy fame,</l>
               <l>My heart is euer muſing on the ſame,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:43"/>
               <l>My tongue would ſtill be buſied with thy praiſe:</l>
               <l>I would mine eyes were blind and could not ſee,</l>
               <l>I would mine eares were deafe and would not heare;</l>
               <l>I would my heart would neuer hold thee deare,</l>
               <l>I would my tongue all ſuch reports would flee:</l>
               <l>Th'eyes in their circles do thy picture hold,</l>
               <l>Th'eares conducts, keepe ſtill ecchoes of thy worth,</l>
               <l>The heart can neuer barre ſweet fancies forth,</l>
               <l>The tongue that which I thinke muſt ſtill vnfold:</l>
               <l>Thy beauties then from which I would rebell,</l>
               <l>Th'eyes ſee, th'eares heare th'heart thinks, and tong muſt tell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 95.</head>
               <l>WHile as th'undanted ſquadrons of my mind,</l>
               <l>On mountaines of deſerts reard high deſires,</l>
               <l>And my proud heart that euermore aſpires,</l>
               <l>To ſcale the heauen of beautie had deſign'd:</l>
               <l>The faire fac'd goddeſſe of that ſtately frame,</l>
               <l>Look'd on my haughtie thoughts with ſcorne a ſpace;</l>
               <l>Then thundred all that proud Gigantike race,</l>
               <l>And from her lightning lights throw'd many a flame.</l>
               <l>Then quite for to confound my loftie cares,</l>
               <l>Euen at the firſt encounter as it chanc'd,</l>
               <l>Th'ouer-daring heart that to th'aſſault aduanc'd,</l>
               <l>Was cou'red with a weight of huge diſpaires,</l>
               <l>Beneath the which the wretch doth ſtill remaine,</l>
               <l>Caſting forth flames of furie and diſdaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 96.</head>
               <l>FAire Tygreſſe tell, contents it not thy ſight,</l>
               <l>To ſee me die each day a thouſand times?</l>
               <l>O how could I commit ſuch monſtrous crimes,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:43"/>
               <l>As merit to this martirdome by night?</l>
               <l>Not onely hath thy wrath adiudg'd to paine,</l>
               <l>This earthly priſon that thy picture keepes,</l>
               <l>But doth the ſoule while as the bodie ſleepes,</l>
               <l>With many fearefull dreames from reſt reſtraine.</l>
               <l>Lo thus I waſte to worke a tyrants will,</l>
               <l>My dayes in torment, and my nights in terror,</l>
               <l>And here confin'd within an endleſſe error,</l>
               <l>Without repentance do perſeuer ſtill:</l>
               <l>That it is hard to iudge though both be loſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe conſtancie or crueltie is moſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 97.</head>
               <l>LOoke to a tyrant what it is to yeeld,</l>
               <l>Who printing ſtill to publiſh my diſgrace,</l>
               <l>The ſtorie of my ouerthrow in my face,</l>
               <l>Erects pale Trophees in that bloudleſſe field:</l>
               <l>The world that viewes this ſtrange triumphall arke,</l>
               <l>Reades in my lookes as lines thy beauties deeds,</l>
               <l>Which in each mind ſo great amazement breeds,</l>
               <l>That I am made of many eyes the marke:</l>
               <l>But what auailes this Tygreſſe triumph, O</l>
               <l>And couldſt thou not be cruell if not knowne,</l>
               <l>But in this meager map it muſt be ſhowne,</l>
               <l>That thou inſultſt to ſee thy ſubiects ſo?</l>
               <l>And my diſgrace it grieues me not ſo much,</l>
               <l>As that it ſhould be ſaid that thou art ſuch.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 98.</head>
               <l>LEt others of the worlds decaying tell,</l>
               <l>I enuy not thoſe of the golden age,</l>
               <l>That did their careleſſe thoughts for nought engage,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:44"/>
               <l>But cloyd with all delights, liu'd long and well:</l>
               <l>And as for me, I mind t'applaud my fate;</l>
               <l>Though I was long in comming to the light,</l>
               <l>Yet may I mount to fortunes higheſt hight,</l>
               <l>So great a good could neuer come too late;</l>
               <l>I'm glad that it was not my chance to liue,</l>
               <l>Till as that heauenly creature firſt was borne,</l>
               <l>Who as an Angell doth the earth adorne,</l>
               <l>And buried vertue in the tombe reuiue:</l>
               <l>For vice ouerflowes the world with ſuch a flood,</l>
               <l>That in it all ſaue ſhe there is no good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sonet,</hi> 99.</head>
               <l>WHilſt curiouſly I gaz'd on beauties skies,</l>
               <l>My ſoule in litle liquid ruſlets runne,</l>
               <l>Like ſnowie mountaines melted with the Sunne,</l>
               <l>Was liquified through force of two faire eyes,</l>
               <l>Thence ſprang pure ſprings and neuer-tainted ſtreames,</l>
               <l>In which a Nymph her image did behold,</l>
               <l>And cruell ſhe (ah that it ſhould be told)</l>
               <l>VVhiles daign'd to grace them with ſome chearfull beames,</l>
               <l>Till once beholding that her ſhadow ſo,</l>
               <l>Made thoſe poore waters partners of her praiſe,</l>
               <l>She by abſtracting of her beauties rayes,</l>
               <l>VVith griefe congeal'd the ſource from whence they flow:</l>
               <l>But through the yce of that vniuſt diſdaine,</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill tranſpares her picture and my paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> l00.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>AVrora</hi> now haue I not cauſe to rage,</l>
               <l>Since all thy fiſhing but a frog hath catch'd?</l>
               <l>May I not mourne to ſee the morning match'd,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:44"/>
               <l>VVith one that's in the euening of his age?</l>
               <l>Should hoary lockes ſad meſſengers of death,</l>
               <l>Sport with thy golden haires in beauties Inne?</l>
               <l>And ſhould that furrow'd face foyle thy ſmooth skinne,</l>
               <l>And bath it ſelfe in th'Ambroſie of thy breath?</l>
               <l>More then mine owne I lament thy miſhaps;</l>
               <l>Muſt he who iealous through his owne defects,</l>
               <l>Thy beauties vnſtaind treaſure ſtill ſuſpects,</l>
               <l>Sleepe on the ſnow-ſwolne pillowes of thy paps,</l>
               <l>VVhile as a lothed burthen in thine armes,</l>
               <l>Doth make thee out of time waile cureleſſe harmes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 101.</head>
               <l>ALL that behold me on thy beauties ſhelfe,</l>
               <l>To caſt my ſelfe away toſs'd with conceit,</l>
               <l>Since thou wilt haue no pitie of my ſtate,</l>
               <l>VVould that I tooke ſome pitie of my ſelfe:</l>
               <l>For what, ſay they, though ſhe diſdaine to bow,</l>
               <l>And takes a pleaſure for to ſee thee ſad,</l>
               <l>Yet there be many a one that would be glad,</l>
               <l>To boſt themſelues of ſuch a one as thou.</l>
               <l>But ah their counſell of ſmall knowledge ſauours,</l>
               <l>For O poore fooles, they ſee not what I ſee,</l>
               <l>Thy frownes are ſweeter then their ſmiles can be,</l>
               <l>The worſt of thy diſdaines worth all their fauours:</l>
               <l>I rather (deare) of thine one looke to haue,</l>
               <l>Then of another all that I would craue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 102.</head>
               <l>WHen as that louely tent of beautie dies,</l>
               <l>And that thou as thine enemie fleeſt thy glaſſe,</l>
               <l>And doeſt with griefe remember what it was,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:45"/>
               <l>That to betray my heart allur'd mine eyes:</l>
               <l>Then hauing bought experience with great paines,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt (although too late) thine errour find,</l>
               <l>Whilſt thou reuolu'ſt in a digeſted mind,</l>
               <l>My faithfull loue, and thy vnkind diſdaines:</l>
               <l>And if that former times might be recald,</l>
               <l>While as thou ſadly ſitſt retir'd alone,</l>
               <l>Then thou wouldſt ſatisfie for all that's gone,</l>
               <l>And I in thy hearts throne would be inſtald:</l>
               <l>Deare, if I know thee of this mind at laſt,</l>
               <l>Ile thinke my ſelfe aueng'd of all that's part.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Elegie</hi> 3.</head>
               <l>IN ſilent horrors here, where neuer mirth remaines,</l>
               <l>I do retire my ſelfe apart, as rage and griefe conſtraines:</l>
               <l>So may I ſigh vnknowne, whilſt other comfort failes,</l>
               <l>An infranchiſed citizen of ſolitarie vales;</l>
               <l>Her priuiledge to plain, ſince nought but plaints ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pleaſe,</l>
               <l>My ſad conceptions I diſcloſe, diſeaſed at my eaſe.</l>
               <l>No barren pitie here my paſſions doth increaſe,</l>
               <l>Nor no detracter here reſorts, deriding my diſtreſſe:</l>
               <l>But wandring through the world, a vagabonding gueſt,</l>
               <l>Acquiring moſt contentment then when I am reſt of reſt.</l>
               <l>Againſt thoſe froward fates, that did my bliſſe controule,</l>
               <l>I thunder forth a thouſand threats in th'anguiſh of my ſoule.</l>
               <l>And lo lunaticke-like do daſh on euery ſhelfe,</l>
               <l>And conuocate a court of cares for to condemne my ſelfe:</l>
               <l>My fancies which in end time doth fantaſticke try,</l>
               <l>I figure forth eſſentially in all the obiects by:</l>
               <l>In euery corner where my reckleſſe eye repaires,</l>
               <l>I reade great volumes of miſhaps, memorials of deſpaires:</l>
               <l>All things that I behold, vpbraid me my eſtate,</l>
               <l>And oft I bluſh within my breſt, aſham'd of my conceit.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:45"/>
               <l>Thoſe branches broken downe with mercie-wanting winds,</l>
               <l>I Obiect me my deiected ſtate, that greater fury finds:</l>
               <l>Their winter-beaten weed diſperſt vpon the plaine,</l>
               <l>Are like to my renounced hopes, all ſcattred with diſdaine.</l>
               <l>Lo wondring at my ſtate the ſtrongeſt torrent ſtayes,</l>
               <l>And turning and returning oft, would ſcorne my crooked wayes.</l>
               <l>In end I find my fate ouer all before my face,</l>
               <l>Enregiſtred eternally in th'annales of diſgrace.</l>
               <l>Thoſe croſſes out of count might make die rockes to riue,</l>
               <l>That this ſmall remanent of life for to extinguiſh ſtriue:</l>
               <l>And yet my rockie heart ſo hardned with miſhaps,</l>
               <l>Now by no meanes can be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mou'd, not with <hi>Ioues</hi> thunder claps:</l>
               <l>But in huge woes inuolu'd with intricating art,</l>
               <l>Surcharg'd with ſorowes I ſuccomb and ſenſleſly do ſmart;</l>
               <l>And in this labyrinth exil'd from all repoſe, breath,</l>
               <l>I conſecrate this curſed corpes a ſacrifice to woes:</l>
               <l>Whilſt many a furious plaint my ſmoaking breaſt ſhall breath,</l>
               <l>Ecclips'd with many a cloudie thought, aggrieu'd vnto the death:</l>
               <l>With th'eccho plac'd beſide ſome ſolitary ſourſe,</l>
               <l>Diſaſtruous accidents ſhall be the ground of our diſcourſe.</l>
               <l>Her maimed words ſhal ſhew how my hurt hart half dies,</l>
               <l>Conſum'd with corroſiues of care, caractred in mine eyes.</l>
               <l>My Muſe ſhall now no more tranſported with reſpects,</l>
               <l>Exalt that euill deſeruing one as fancie ſtill directs:</l>
               <l>Nor yet no partiall pen ſhall ſpot her ſpotleſſe fame,</l>
               <l>Vnhoneſtly diſhonoring an honorable name.</l>
               <l>But I ſhall ſadly ſing, too tragickly inclin'd,</l>
               <l>Some ſubiect ſympathizing with my melancholious mind.</l>
               <l>Nor will I more deſcribe my dayly deadly ſtrife,</l>
               <l>My publike wrongs, my priuate woes, miſlucks in loue and life:</l>
               <l>That would but vexe the world for to extend my toiles,</l>
               <l>In painting forth particularly my many formes of foiles.</l>
               <l>No, none in ſpeciall I purpoſe to bewray,</l>
               <l>But one as all, and all as one, I mind to mourne for ay.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:46"/>
               <l>For being iuſtly weigh'd, the leaſt that I lament,</l>
               <l>Deſerues indeed to be bewail'd, til th'vſe of th'eyes be ſpent;</l>
               <l>And ſince I ſhould the leaſt perpetually deplore,</l>
               <l>The moſt again though maruellous, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be bemon'd no more</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 103.</head>
               <l>TO yeeld to thoſe I cannot but diſdaine,</l>
               <l>Whoſe face doth but entangle fooliſh hearts;</l>
               <l>It is the beautie of the better parts,</l>
               <l>With which I mind my fancies for to chaine.</l>
               <l>Thoſe that haue nought wherewith mens minds to gaine,</l>
               <l>But onely curled lockes and wanton lookes,</l>
               <l>Are but like fleeting baites that haue no hookes,</l>
               <l>Which may well take, but cannot well retaine:</l>
               <l>He that began to yeeld to th'outward grace,</l>
               <l>And then the treaſures of the mind doth proue:</l>
               <l>He, who as t'were was with the maske in loue,</l>
               <l>What doth he thinke when as he ſees the face?</l>
               <l>No doubt being lim'd by th'outward colours ſo,</l>
               <l>That inward worth would neuer let him go.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 104.</head>
               <l>LOng time I did thy cruelties deteſt,</l>
               <l>And blaz'd thy rigor in a thouſand lines;</l>
               <l>But now through my complaints thy vertue ſhines,</l>
               <l>That was but working all things for the beſt:</l>
               <l>Thou of my raſh affections held'ſt the raines,</l>
               <l>And ſpying dangerous ſparkes come from my fires,</l>
               <l>Didſt wiſely temper my enflam'd deſires,</l>
               <l>VVith ſome chaſt fauours, mixt with ſweet diſdaines:</l>
               <l>And when thou ſaw'ſt I did all hope deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>And look'd like one that wreſtled with deſpaire,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:46"/>
               <l>Then of my ſafetie thy exceeding care,</l>
               <l>Shew'd that I kept thine heart, thou but thine eyes:</l>
               <l>For whilſt thy reaſon did thy fancies tame,</l>
               <l>I ſaw the ſmoke, although thou hidſt the flame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 105.</head>
               <l>SHould I the treaſure of my life betake,</l>
               <l>To thought-toſs'd breath whoſe babling might it marre,</l>
               <l>VVords with affection wing'd might flee too farre,</l>
               <l>And once ſent forth can neuer be brought backe:</l>
               <l>Nor will I truſt mine eyes, whoſe partiall lookes</l>
               <l>Haue oft conſpir'd for to betray my mind,</l>
               <l>And would their light ſtill to one obiect bind,</l>
               <l>VVhile as the fornace of my boſome ſmokes:</l>
               <l>No, no, my loue, and that which makes me thrall,</l>
               <l>Shall onely be entruſted to my ſoule,</l>
               <l>So may I ſtray, yet none my courſe controule,</l>
               <l>VVhilſt though orethrowne, none triumphs for my fall:</l>
               <l>My thoughts while as confin'd within my breſt,</l>
               <l>Shall onely priuie to my paſſions reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Son.</hi> 106.</head>
               <l>A Wake my Muſe, and leaue to dreame of loues,</l>
               <l>Shake off ſoft fancies chaines, I muſt be free,</l>
               <l>Ile parch no more, vpon the mirtle tree,</l>
               <l>Nor glide through th'aire with beauties ſacred doues;</l>
               <l>But with <hi>Ioues</hi> ſlately bird Ile leaue my neſt,</l>
               <l>And trie my ſight againſt <hi>Apolloes</hi> raies:</l>
               <l>Then if that ought my ventrous courſe diſmaies,</l>
               <l>Vpon the Oliues boughes Ile light and reſt:</l>
               <l>Ile tune my accents to a trumpet now,</l>
               <l>And ſeeke the Laurell in another field,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:47"/>
               <l>Thus I that once, as Beautie meanes did yeeld,</l>
               <l>Did diuers garments on my thoughts beſtow:</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Icarus</hi> I feare, vnwiſely bold,</l>
               <l>Am purpos'd others paſſions now t'vnfold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Song.</hi> 10.</head>
               <l>FArewell ſweet fancies, and once deare delights,</l>
               <l>The treaſures of my life, which made me proue</l>
               <l>That vnaccompliſh'd ioy that charm'd the ſprights,</l>
               <l>And whilſt by it I onely ſeem'd to moue,</l>
               <l>Did hold my rauiſh'd ſoule, big with deſire,</l>
               <l>That taſting thoſe, to greater did aſpire.</l>
               <l>Farewell free thraldome, freedome that was thrall,</l>
               <l>While as I led a ſolitary life,</l>
               <l>Yet neuer leſſe alone, whilſt arm'd for all,</l>
               <l>My thoughts were buſied with an endleſſe ſtrife:</l>
               <l>For then not hauing bound my ſelfe to any,</l>
               <l>I being bound to none, was bound to many.</l>
               <l>Great God that tam'ſt the gods old-witted child,</l>
               <l>Whoſe temples breſts, whoſe altars are mens hearts.</l>
               <l>From my hearts fort thy legions are exild,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Hymens</hi> torch hath burn'd out all thy darts:</l>
               <l>Since I in end haue bound my ſelfe to one,</l>
               <l>That by this meanes I may be bound to none.</l>
               <l>Thou daintie goddeſſe with the ſoft white skinne,</l>
               <l>To whom ſo many offrings dayly ſmoke,</l>
               <l>Were beauties proceſſe yet for to begin,</l>
               <l>That ſentence I would labour to reuoke:</l>
               <l>Which on mount Ida as thy ſmiles did charme,</l>
               <l>The Phrigian ſhepheard gaue to his owne harme.</l>
               <l>And if the queſtion were referd to mee,</l>
               <l>On whom I would beſtow the ball of gold,</l>
               <l>I feare me <hi>Venus</hi> ſhould be laſt of three,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:598:47"/>
               <l>For with the Thunderers ſiſter I would hold,</l>
               <l>Whoſe honeſt flames pent in a lawfull bounds,</l>
               <l>No feare diſturbs, nor yet no ſhame confounds.</l>
               <l>I mind to ſpeake no more of beauties Doue,</l>
               <l>The Peacocke is the bird whoſe fame Ile raiſe;</l>
               <l>Not that I <hi>Argos</hi> need to watch my loue,</l>
               <l>But ſo his miſtris <hi>Iuno</hi> for to praiſe:</l>
               <l>And if I with his eyes, then it ſhall be,</l>
               <l>That I with many eyes my loue may ſee</l>
               <l>Then farewell croſſing ioyes, and ioyfull croſſes,</l>
               <l>Moſt bitter ſweets, and yet moſt ſugred ſowers,</l>
               <l>Moſt hurtfull gaines, yet moſt commodious loſſes,</l>
               <l>That made my yeares to flee away like howers,</l>
               <l>And ſpent the ſpring time of mine age in vaine,</l>
               <l>Which now my ſummer muſt redeeme againe.</l>
               <l>O welcome eaſie yoke, ſweet bondage come,</l>
               <l>I ſeeke not from thy toiles for to be ſhielded,</l>
               <l>But I am well content to be orecome,</l>
               <l>Since that I muſt commaund when I haue yeelded:</l>
               <l>Then here I quit both <hi>Cupid</hi> and his mother,</l>
               <l>And do reſigne my ſelfe t'obtaine another.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
